Welcome, everyone. Welcome to our session.
We're excited to be here today and talk about publishing and communications,
sharing the ideas we have for this,
and hopefully it sparks some conversations that also continue at
our unconference. So with that, I would like to welcome
our first speaker,
David Fischmuller.
Thank you.
And
thank you all for being here at such an early hour on the last
day. So I'm going to talk about tracking
research activities in taxonomy.
Maybe some of you have
been to the garden and seen that building or have paid attention to the
introduction on Monday.
Yeah.
So, let's look at what's going on
in there for research activities.
So I'm going to talk about the Tetrix project.
Maybe some of you have seen the banner down at the Pensoft booth.
The thing is, the Tetrix project has just started in the beginning of
this month, so there's not really much to talk about this in terms of outcome
yet, but that doesn't matter. I'm going to tell you what we have
planned and our approaches and methodologies,
and most importantly, we want your feedback, which is why I'm here in the first
place.
So what is Tetrix?
As I said, you might have seen the logo already during this conference.
Tetrix as a project, stands as a typical project acronym,
Tetrix, Next Level for the Taxonomy of Tomorrow.
And when you look at it, you see there's another acronym in there, TETRIS.
Maybe some of you have seen that logo before.
So,
that was another project, and stands for
Transforming European Taxonomy through Training, Research, and Innovations.
So Tetrix is the successor project of TETRIS,
and both are EU-funded projects to improve the systems and
landscape for taxonomic research
in Europe, special focus, but not necessarily only.
So and within the Tetrix project, work package one
has the goal to automatically gather ongoing
taxonomic research activities across different sources
and store those information in a central place and
align them with taxonomic backbones,
deliver insights based on those
outcomes that will guide future funding
priorities,
policymaking maybe,
but also collaborations between the public and private sector.
So we didn't start out from scratch.
We had some previous work to rely on.
Most notably,
during TETRIS, there was one task that was
focusing on taxonomic expertise in Europe.
So that's a smaller segment of what we are going to do now, but
still,
there we had two approaches. One was based on taxonomic
publications. So this was done by the colleagues at the Botanic Garden in Meise,
and they used the
paper search engine Open Alex to filter for
publications in the field of taxonomy based on certain keywords,
and then processed the data and
got some really nice results showing
who is actively researching.
The second approach was based on specimens.
That was done at the Botanic Garden in Berlin, mainly by me.
And there we used specimen data from GBIF and processing
steps were a bit more elaborate there.
We also weren't quite as successful as the colleagues in Meise because
the data we relied on The person data coming
from GBIF was a bit ambiguous, and there were
very few identifiers to rely on, so that was a bit more tricky.
But yeah, those were the things we have already done,
which will now feed into our approach here.
The three tasks I previously mentioned align very
well with the three tasks within the work package.
So we have the resource identification,
aggregation and curation, and evaluation and presentation.
So
for the resource identification in the project proposal,
we have five
main
parts. We have the taxonomic publication databases, we
have funding records and project registries,
taxonomic data networks, resources on dark data, and
expertise and services, and then everything else, which is also kind of
why I'm here, the other sources opening up.
All of this will feed into the central database
called TaxoTrack,
where we then align that information with taxonomic backbones,
but also other
external identifiers like Wikidata, ROA, ORCID.
And then we produce the outcomes. It could be maps showing
distributions of research activities, taxonomic evaluations, so
which parts of the taxonomic tree are actively being worked on, which ones
are understudied,
maybe policy briefs or some interactive dashboards, things like
that,
that all rely on the data previously gathered.
So now let's look a bit further into the resources.
So for the publication databases, this sub-task will be done by
the colleagues at Pensoft,
and they will
rely on the Tetris approach but go beyond.
They also look into sub-article level data, so
particularly the Biodiversity Literature Repository,
Biodiversity PMC Database, and the OpenBioDiv Database.
All three of them were also developed or heavily worked on
during the Bicycle project, so we have another connection to previous projects
here.
For the funding record and project registries, the colleagues at the UFT
Leipzig are responsible.
And there they want to look at which areas of
research are actively being funded, both on international,
national, and regional levels,
but also non-governmental funding, so industry collaborations or maybe money
from foundations.
The taxonomic data networks task done by us
and the Botanical Garden in Meise and the Institute of Botany in
Prague,
Czech Academy of Sciences.
So we there have a plethora of different sources, taxonomic
backbones, name registries. So trying to track what is
changing there, what's
new, checklist banks, but also data networks,
and especially the colleagues from Prague
want to put a special focus on Central and Eastern European sources
and want to start with a Pleiades database.
For the resources on dark data, the colleagues here in Norway, Norwegian University
of Science and Technology,
looking into that.
But there, the research landscape is not as well captured with the conventional
sources that we've looked at so far,
and so they want to particularly focus on detecting and linking pre-named
taxonomic activities. So things that are going on before the
taxons to get the name and connect this to researchers, institutions,
taxon, and geographic regions.
But they also want to use DNA barcoding, bins, images,
species hypothesis, and inventories.
And for the expertise and services, this is where we
rely on the previous works as well.
During the Tetris project, there was a marketplace created and had
the sections of expertise and services.
And so the colleagues, again from Pensoft, but also from CITAV and Senckenberg,
are continuing to work on that in Tetrix in the work package four.
So there will be a close interaction there and seeing, okay, who
has expertise or which services are being
provided,
but also align it with the work from the CITAV
scientific research group.
And then we go to the other sources.
So
there could be things we haven't considered yet that are not explicitly
part of the proposal. Maybe it's worth looking into social media
for scientific resources. Maybe it's
worth looking at citizen science or research software that's
dedicated to special taxonomic groups.
But also we are open for other ideas.
So if you have any, please let us know.
So regarding ideas, so what have we missed here?
And especially if you work in taxonomy, how would we
detect your research? So would it show up in any of the sources
mentioned, or would
your work take a different way? How can we track that?
So your ideas are welcome.
I
want to have a discussion. We have a few more minutes left during the time slot.
But also we created a survey with particular focus for the funding
agencies and project registries.
So I know that there are a lot of national
or even regional funding agencies, so
we would like to hear from them also in terms of prioritization.
Which ones are the ones that are actually funding work in your
country?
And so we created the survey. But there's also a
section for other ideas and researchers.
So you can just skip the entire first two sections if you don't have anything
to say about
funding agencies or project registries, and just
fill out the last part where it's Pretty open format and you can
enter your ideas.
I'm going to go back to this slide in a second, but first,
before we now start the discussion, thank you for your attention.
And I want to thank
my co-authors, Jana Hoffmann and Anton Genschow, already left.
But also Emily Hartrop, Hannah Honka, Luba Penev,
and Jan Walk for their inputs in this
session. And so
if you have any further ideas, just send me an email or contact me here or
Huva or TEDx Slack.
And now just the obligatory image sources.
Just a fun little fact, all of the people who are represented
as botanists in the images, the images are always called "The Botanist,"
with the exception of the guy who's drinking.
He's "The Satisfied Botanist."
Yeah. And so,
I'm open for your ideas and discussions.
Your turn.
Not for me.
So, David, I love your question. I posted a similar
one in the-
Yeah
... chat online, which is what can we do?
So for those of you who don't know, so the project I work on,
the Species File group, one of the software products we work on is TaxonWorks.
So many, the global species database groups, Orthoptera Species
File,
Treehoppers, there's lots of people managing their nomenclature for their
research in our software that ends up in Catalog of Life.
So the question is what could we be doing in our publications, I think to me, to
you, that you can think of? Are there things that as publishers
we could be doing?
Our idea is more that you
wouldn't necessarily need to change your workflows.
Maybe that's-
Mm-hmm
...
a later part, but for now, we would just want to
get started into tracking what is going
on. And as I said, the project has just started.
We have the kickoff meeting in two weeks.
So there hasn't been much work done except for
the previous project. So, we are going to get the different
sources-
Right
... and then have to align them.
But also,
need to
set priorities. So which
publishers to first get the information from, which databases to focus
on.
And ideally, if
there are any things that we notice that, oh, yeah, there's
certain activities we just cannot track with our approach,
then it would be interesting to see whether
maybe it's worth for you just to use one of the
previously covered channels-
Mm-hmm
... or whether it's up to us
to get that information in some other way.
Okay.
And so ideally, everything should be machine accessible so we can
run this analysis every couple of weeks or
months.
Yeah.
But
we don't
expect other people to change their publication methods
to align with our projects instead of we getting the information.
Okay.
Yeah.
Oh, good.
And I can maybe also-
The floor mic, please.
Yeah. So maybe to answer your question, we talked about that
yesterday with the Pensoff folks.
And the simplest thing that we really need for doing
these kinds of analysis is providing the taxonomists that publish their
work are providing ORCIDs.
Simple, I know, but if you look at sometimes the publications, they still
do not have ORCIDs.
Okay.
And that's a big problem.
Okay, cool.
So that's one of the things that we need to actually gather all the information,
especially when it's on personal level. So that can be super helpful, yeah.
Yeah.
And then register your taxonomic kind of acts
in the respective databases, like ZooBank and that kind of stuff or,
sorry, I'm zoologist by training so-
Yeah
... I know the botanists are way better on that.
So these very simple things help a lot.
Yeah.
And
David, I know we were talking about this, but it just came to me.
One great source is going to be institutional reports
for evaluation.
Yeah.
I never thought about it, but I remember we have to report the number of species
that we
describe as institutions because-
Mm-hmm
... it's kind of a flagship, we have to say, are that and many.
Sure.
So that would be a really good thing to just-
It's a thing we should have thought of this
... warning here.
Of course. We do one as well.
Yes.
Yep. So we're out of time, but-
Yeah
... now it's started. Come to the unconference, continue the conversation, join
the survey. Yes. Fine, David, there you go. Thank you.
Yes, thank
you. Next,
I'd like to welcome Melissa Chin-Yi Lu.
Yes.
All right. Thank you.
Thank you.
Good morning, everyone. I'm Melissa from Taiwan,
and today I will share how Taipei
developed a
collaborator training system, called TaipeiFIRST.
And before that, let me introduce a bit about TaipeiF.
TaipeiF is the Taiwan Biodiversity Information Facility,
the GBIF node in Taiwan. And like what
other GBIF nodes do, we help
the local biodiversity community mobilize,
standardize, publish, and reuse the open biodiversity
data. And our work includes data
publishing support, infrastructure and tool
development, training events organizing, and
open data promotion, and also
data use support.
And Taipei has invested these works and the
community engagement for many years.
So more and more people and organizations are willing to
publish and use biodiversity data.
But it also exposed a
capacity gap and requests
range from the basic questions
to detailed data cleaning, translation, and also
taxonomic validation. And these tasks
required different kinds of expertise.
And we are just a small node team,
we have not enough capacity to
cover all of them.
So we therefore started to think about how
training could create a reliable pool of
collaborators ready to take on assignments.
So what we have done is to build out a system
for training new collaborators, which is called
TaipeiFIRT. And it is inspired by the GBIF
volunteer community model, and it creates
a clear path from learning to practice.
And participants first complete a full Taipei
workshop, and they then pass the required
assignments. And after they earn the advanced certificates,
each role has an additional practical
assessment.
So successful participants become eligible for a paid
collaboration when a suitable task becomes available.
And this connection matters because the
certificates represent demonstrated ability,
while the paid work gives participants experience and
recognizes their contribution.
So Taipei coordinates assignments and matches
collaborators according to their background and
expertise and interests.
And TaipeiFIRT includes four
roles that cover different parts of the
data mobilization workflow. And translators
make the international technical resources,
most of that they are from GBIF articles and
documents available in traditional Chinese.
And ambassador
support workshops as a mentor and may later
become a trainer also.
And data mobilizer
help institutions clean and
prepare datasets for publication.
And species name checkers contribute taxonomic
information to the Catalog of Life in Taiwan.
We also call it Taicol.
Okay. And separating the roles allows
people to contribute through their strongest
skills. It also lets Taipei set relevant
assessment and criteria instead of expecting every
collaborator to master the entire workflow.
And all collaborators begin with a shared
training backbone. For most of roles, this
is Taipei's biodiversity data publishing and data
use workshop. But the species name checkers use the
Taicol workshop.
And the common assignments that cover the practical skills
that Taipei needs collaborators to understand.
For example, Darwin Core mapping,
structuring a sampling event, a
dataset, and publishing through a test IPT,
and cleaning data in OpenRefine,
and searching data on GBIF to find answers to
some advanced questions.
So participants submit the assignments after the workshop,
and trainer will score them against the defined
rubrics. So this common foundation gives
Taipei confidence that certified collaborators
understand the same best basic concepts
and the workflow.
So after the shared course requirements, each role has a
practical assessment that reflects future assignments.
Like translators complete a trial translation,
and ambassadors first serve as
trainee teaching assistants.
And while those who want to become trainer can also
complete a teaching trial.
And data mobilizers work through a scenario-based
publishing exercise using a supply dataset.
And species name checker must add records or
update scientific name usage in Taicol.
So since late 2022, Taipei has
trained 11 translators,
21 ambassadors, and 11 data mobilizers,
and 19 species name checkers. And
together that is totally
62 collaborators. Okay. And the
largest group is currently the ambassador
community, while that reflects the continuing importance of
workshops and peer support.
But actually, the data mobilizer role has the
most applicants. But it is not
really easy to meet the assessment
qualifications.
Okay. So the collaborators network is already
supporting concrete work, and translators have helped
localize the professional resources mostly from GBIF,
and ambassadors assist during workshops and can
develop toward trainer roles.
And data mobilizers support customized data
cleaning and publication cases.
Maybe most are from
public sectors or even private sectors.
And while species name checkers improve the
taxonomic content of the typo.
And these contributions extend the reach of
our node team or core team, and also create a feedback
loop. And collaborators apply what they learn,
and encounter real issues, and bring practical
experience back into future training and
community.
And
paid assignments recognize that these services
require time, responsibility, and expertise.
And
there are still some challenges for the management
of the TypeBIFR system. The first is,
actually, we need another
capacity to manage the cases and match
between publishers and the TypeBIFRs.
And the second is,
actually key, the sustainability
of the community is not really easy.
Guess we need to think about some incentives to
prevent TypeBIFRs dropping off.
And we also need continuous
fundings. It is the most important part, actually, to
support the system,
especially for the translators and the ambassadors.
So if we
only rely on the TypeBIFR system, it's the
humans only support,
there will always have limitations.
So we use the tools to fill the gap in human
capacity. So the first tool is
the Digital TypeBIFR.
And it's
24/7 AI helper for answering open
data related questions and help organize
datasets. And another one is TypeBIFR Open Data
Toolkit. It's an all-in-one dataset
preparation tool from data template generating, data
organizing, validating, and to cleaning.
So to conclude,
a trained community and a system with AI
tools can extend the reach of a small node team.
So we are grateful to all of our
TypeBIFRs and the GBIF volunteer community that
inspired this approach. So thanks for
attention.
Thanks very much, Melissa.
Thank you.
There may be a question or two for you.
Yes.
An insight? Yes.
I think it's a really interesting approach with the different roles and just
have people specialize. So there are four really
good and well-defined roles. But if you had to add one or
two more, which other topics would you cover next?
Wow.
I will think about my capacity, actually, because
it's most of me to manage all the TypeBIFRs.
Let me think about.
I think I'll
maybe ask,
the next would be to let trainers trying to
develop
maybe new training courses with our team together.
Because there are more and more new concept, like new data model, data
package, or a humble extension thing.
We need some design of the training courses in
traditional Chinese, so I may need that kind of-
Right
... yeah, roles.
I think there's time for one more. Oh, yeah. Esteban.
Thank you very much, Melissa. Very interesting.
Have you had any problems with hallucinations of the
24/7 AI helper, like people get
confused and get back to you, like, "Okay, this is not working,"
or it so far works for their intended purposes?
Actually, we try to test them.
We
promote this tool mostly in the workshop, and we let the
participants try to use that during our exercise part.
And some of them just try it, and I think it matches
about at least 90% of the correction.
Actually, that tool
won the GBIF App Nielsen challenge before.
And we just train more and more the resource from GBIF.
So, so far, I think it works quite well.
I think. Yeah.
Do we have time for one more, or are we...
If you want to.
During the switch?
Yeah.
Okay. Yeah. So the next speaker can
get a headset.
I've got the headset.
Yes. So I have really quick question
or thought. So GBIF has this very lovely model
for helping nodes do the kind of thing that you're doing.
What might be needed in terms of an
additional
workshop or something to talk about how you do-- You've reached
this peak where you've got all these parts working, but you've realized there's
the overhead of making it sustain itself.
So what are the options for that model?
What good things that you could be doing, and maybe the different models could
talk with what they're doing in that same space together.
Yes, I think that's also what I need to do for the future
work.
Yeah.
I need to think about that, actually.
Yes, I'm
also worried about the capacity part.
Yeah.
It's a known issue throughout our community when we do these things, but talking
about what's working for different models to expand-
Yes
... your capabilities, yeah.
Thank you.
Sure.
Ready to go, Siobhan?
Yep.
Okay. Siobhan Leachman.
Hi, everyone. I'm Siobhan Leachman.
I'm a Wikimedian, data curator, and community scientist from New Zealand.
I'm going to be talking to you today about how you can use tools such
as Wikidata, Binomia, Scholia, and Zenodo to improve
the findability and visibility of biodiversity contributions.
So I'm going to start with Wikidata, because in my opinion, this is the one ring to
rule them all, a platform that can help promote biodiversity data and
the people and institutions that help create that data.
Now, as I'm sure you're aware, Wikidata is a free, open knowledge
base, and it acts as the data backbone to Wikipedia.
It stores structured data that are human and machine readable.
Anyone can edit Wikidata. It's multilingual by design and can be read and
edited by humans and applications.
The data can be queried, and as it's openly licensed under a Creative Commons
Zero license, it can be reused without restriction.
Wikidata also acts as a hub for identifiers for other
databases, catalogs, and websites.
Now, it contains items on all sorts of biodiversity
data, as well as information about those who contribute to biodiversity
knowledge. And this includes items about people, taxa, publications of
all types, institutions such as libraries, archives, natural history
museums, as well as items about collections and research expeditions,
to name but a few.
And the items and data contained in Wikidata are all semantically linked to
each other, and this results in data that is easy to find,
extract, and reuse. Multiple internet search engines,
AI applications, biodiversity websites, databases,
collection management systems, and catalogs either link to or reuse
Wikidata. So adding biodiversity contributions and
contributors to Wikidata is a fabulous first step
in improving the findability of access to and
reuse of biodiversity information and can increase the impact
of biodiversity contributions and the impact of the contributors of
those contributions.
Now, I just want to touch on the identifier hub aspect of Wikidata,
because in my view, this is one of its most important attributes.
Wikidata links to over 7,500 other websites,
catalogs, and databases, and in this slide, you can see
just some of the identifiers added to a Wikidata item
for a deceased botanist. And the text is small because there
are just so many identifiers listed on her item.
So here, Wikidata is acting as a bridge between one institution's data
and another institution's data, raising the visibility of all these
linked repositories and the data that's contained within them.
And the identifier hub aspect helps databases and catalogs
to reuse and round-trip that data and the identifiers
attached to relevant Wikidata items.
Now, to give just two examples, the Biodiversity Heritage Library and also the
CTAF botany pilot have pulled information about people
from Wikidata and display that information on their catalog.
And they can do this because identifiers have been placed on the relevant
Wikidata items, which then assist these catalogs to link to
or ingest this data. And this type of reuse,
again, helps raise the visibility of biodiversity data, be it about
people, publications, institutions, locations,
taxa, and so on.
And there's also multiple tools that are built on or reuse
Wikidata that can be used to help broadcast biodiversity
contributions, and I'm just going to deal with three examples today.
The first, and in my view, one of the most important tools for
raising awareness of the work of natural history specimen collectors and
determiners is Binomia.
Now, Binomia helps link specimen occurrence data in GBIF to
either the Wikidata item for a deceased person or the ORCID identifier
for a living person that collected or identified specimens.
And once attributions are made to that person's identifier,
Binomia can then generate a profile, which provides maps,
co-collector networks, lists of institutions that house those specimens,
as well as links to literature citing those specimens.
And the Binomia ID for that collector or determiner can be added
back into Wikidata, completing the data round trip.
Binomia also allows you to create a profile for yourself if you
are a collector or a determiner of natural history specimens, the data of
which is contained in GBIF.
You'll need an ORCID to log into the site, and then you can link specimens that
you've collected or identified to your Binomia profile.
And here, you can see my Binomia profile, which is linked to the grand
total of two specimens that I have collected that have occurrence data
in GBIF.
And Binomia empowers users to archive their collection and
determination data into Zenodo. Once set up, Binomia
auto deposits versioned archives of users' claimed specimen
records. Binomia will generate a freely accessible data set entry in
Zenodo, and it links that Zenodo entry to the user's ORCID ID,
provides a citation, and importantly, a DataCite DOI.
Now, if a Binomia user configures their ORCID profile to accept the
DataCite platform as a trusted party, their new data set
will automatically be added to their ORCID, increasing both the
visibility and documenting the impact of the vital work that
they have undertaken by collecting or identifying natural
history specimens.
Now, Binomia also provides a profile for each GBIF occurrence
data set published by an institution, and here you can see Te
Papa, that's the National Museum of New Zealand's herbarium data
set. Binomia generates frictionless data packages, providing
files generated from those Binomia attributions, and these
generated files can assist institutions to round trip
identifiers, highlight potential data errors, helping
the institution to actually clean their data.
Other Binomia generated files can help to bring to light publications
that have been using the institution's occurrence data, highlighting the
impact of the collection on research.
And as you can see, the Binomia profile provides multiple ways to
increase
visibility and impact of both individual and
institutional contributions to biodiversity knowledge.
Now, another tool that uses Wikidata, and can help improve the accessibility and
visibility of work undertaken by academics is called
Scholia. Scholia is an open source scholarly
profile tool that provides visualizations on data
sourced from Wikidata. It can be used to create visual
scholarly profiles, not just for academics, but also on
all different types of topics, things for people,
organizations, and so much more. So when used for
academic authors, you can obtain detailed scholarly profiles
for their academic contributions.
And in this slide, for example, you can see just one Scholia
visualization for the academic's co-author graph.
Improving the data about biodiversity related scholarly
outputs in Wikidata will both improve the Scholia
profile for those who created those outputs and will
increase the discoverability for others.
Here's another example of a Scholia profile, this time for a publication
that I co-authored, and you can see this visualization links the
publication to my and my fellow co-authors' Wikidata items.
It gives the main subjects as listed in the Wikidata item for that
publication and gives the paper's copyright status and
license. Importantly, you can also see the profile shows all the
links to the Wikidata items for the works cited in our
paper, helping improve the impact metrics of those cited
articles.
It's also possible to link the scholarly article items to Wikidata
items for datasets or natural history collections used in the
production of those publications.
And you can do this by adding to the publication item a users
or an acknowledges statement linking to the relevant Wikidata item for the
collection or the dataset that was used.
This linking can, again, improve the visibility of the natural history
collection, as well as highlight the impact of collections and their
datasets used in research. Now, during my recent Wikimedian
in residence position at the Bioeconomy Science Institute, I
produced documentation to assist those wanting to add their scholarly
publications to Wikidata and also support those who want to
ensure credit is given to natural history collections used to
help produce this research.
The third tool I want to highlight is Expeditia.
Now, this tool visualizes research expeditions, providing
interactive maps with chronological itineraries and
links to relevant natural history specimen records.
Expeditia creates these expedition profiles using
data sourced from Wikidata, GBIF, Binomia, and
georeference.it. By linking and visualizing
research expedition data, Expeditia helps raise
awareness and can expose new audiences to research
expeditions and their important contributions to biodiversity
knowledge.
Now, Binomia, Scholia, and Expeditia are just three examples
of tools that make use of Wikidata to help broadcast biodiversity
contributions. But I just want to point out one more tool that
I and my co-collaborators have used to collate and link publications,
presentations, and datasets that we've created for various
biodiversity related projects. Like Binomia, we
also use Zenodo. Zenodo is a free open
access online archive hosted by CERN.
You can upload documents, spreadsheets, and datasets into this repository.
If needed, it'll generate a DOI for your upload, which can assist with the
linking of this content in other platforms, including
Wikidata.
Zenodo also gives you impact metrics on the number of views and
downloads of your contributions.
You can also create Zenodo communities.
Now, this is useful when collaborating with others, as a Zenodo community
collates the uploads from different creators all in one place.
And in this slide, you can see a Zenodo community my colleagues and I created for
our outreach efforts at the International Botanical Congress in 2024.
We could point interested parties to this collection, empowering
them to explore and reuse any of it at their leisure.
So thank you for listening, and I encourage you to consider how you
might use Wikidata and any of its associated tools and repositories it
supports to increase the impact of your and your
institution's biodiversity contributions. I look forward to your questions.
Thanks so much, Chauvan.
Questions for Chauvan? Insights? Yes, Dmitri.
Ellie's bringing you a mic. Thank you, Ellie.
Thank you. This is fantastic. When David presented Binomia and
Biodiversity Next,
I was suggesting to him to consider that every single
natural history explorer leaves a linear
trace of activities.
Mm-hmm.
Not so much around cradle and not so much around gravestone, but in between, when
we're most active. Specimens, identifications, expeditions, field
notes, and so on.
Yes.
And they sit like differently colored beads on a single thread.
Now with sensors, you can parallelize.
You can deploy five sensors at a time, then
your thread becomes a bit thicker.
So I think what you presented is just fantastic, and I think there is an
opportunity to
further connect work at Wikimedia and BHL and specimens
and sequences and images in Flickr and whatnot in a single
digital trace of the researcher. There are all kind of privacy concerns, and I'm
not sure how close or open certain people will be to that.
I would like to hear your opinion about this threads idea.
Yeah. When it comes to Wikidata, it's like Wikipedia.
You need citable sources.
And you also need editors who are aware of the privacy side
of things. So I'm careful that when I put data about living
people in, I, tell you the truth, tend to concentrate on dead people because it's a
lot easier. But if I do deal with living people, I normally
look at their ORCID and what they are releasing themselves.
Okay.
And so if they've got it on their ORCID, then I'm happy to put it into
Wikidata because it's public. If their ORCID is closed,
sometimes I can still link their ORCID because that identifier is still really
important for, say, a publication.
They may have put their ORCID on a publication, and I can disambiguate that person.
But I won't add anything that's not publicly available. Yeah.
Maybe just a quick reaction to this.
The privacy I'm talking about is not like, where is your garden?
Not
personal privacy, but professional researcher privacy.
Pressures like digital sequence information and Nagoya Protocol-
Yeah
...
they
sometimes work against the data openness.
Mm.
And
we can generate much more biodiversity evidence than the current
legislative framework allows.
Mm.
Some of us don't go this way. I'm not collecting in
the countries I'm visiting on GBIF trips because I'm working for GBIF, and I don't
want to break any rules. I can't in my role.
Mm.
If I would be working in university, I would reconsider this practice.
But my museum curator will
refuse the specimens collected in a fishy manner.
Yeah.
Binomia is
actually revealing such decisions very transparently.
Yeah.
This is the privacy I'm talking about.
Yeah. Well, when it comes to Binomia,
for a start, Binomia only uses Wikidata for deceased people.
And the privacy in relation to specimens, yeah,
it has to be on GBIF. Again, it has to be published before we use it.
So if it's not published-
Yeah
... Wikidata won't pick it up anyway.
Exactly.
Yeah, and Binomia won't pick it up. Yeah.
Okay, cool. Thank you. Oh, and there's somebody in the other-
Oh, and there's somebody in the other-
Very quick. Very quick, like one minute total.
Very quick question. So I'm curious about how you've possibly
used Wikidata or the Binomia to track people who are working
with the collection. So their interactions aren't actually collecting, but doing
the repairs and the cataloging and that kind of more-
Yeah, that's not covered by Binomia.
Yeah.
No, unfortunately.
It's okay.
Can I jump in?
Yes.
Yeah.
So expanding the concept, yes. It's so exciting.
So another example I was going to add very quickly.
There is a project right now going on at WoRMS, the World Online
Marine...
Register.
Yes. Register.
Yeah. System. Something.
World Online Register of Marine Species.
Species.
There we go. And they are
going back and trying to put identifiers, Q numbers, and
ORCIDs on authors of taxon names.
Yeah.
So we'd want to add, this is the roles I spoke about in my talk.
So we've got the role of collector and the role of identifier.
Mm-hmm.
You've got the role of conservator, the role of whatever, and you could imagine the
same thing. And with that, I have to be quiet.
There's actually a Wikidata project that I'm involved in for that particular piece
of work, so if anyone wants to join us in doing that, come talk to me.
I'd love more co-collaborators.
Okay.
Thank you.
Yes. Thank you. And thank you for your question.
This last one up right here.
Yes.
Next up.
Evidence has a structure. Can you-- Yeah. Thank you.
I prepared my presentation as a video, which will be played now in front of you,
but with me present in the room for discussion questions.
I'm talking once again about things I don't fully understand, so
I'm not sure it's a bigger or less embarrassment to do it as a video, but here we
go. Thank you.
Dmitri,
take-
Hello.
My name is Dmitri Shigal. I work in GBIF Secretariat, and in this
presentation, I would like to offer some
thoughts on handling evidence and a cross-disciplinary perspective.
Evidence has a structure.
In biodiversity data recording, we mostly deal with empirical evidence,
although intellectual evidence exists and coexists with empirical.
Also, we often have direct and circumstantial evidence,
sometimes in combination, like in this picture
Images of the wasp individuals is an example of direct evidence with many
possible inferences, including on their count and abundance,
population size maybe.
And then their paper nest, which is circumstantial evidence.
Even without wasps in the image, it would imply a breeding population.
We have three steps in this process.
We have detection, we have interpretation, and then we
register both of them. Registration sits in the middle, and it's pulled by both
sides. And this is the step
that our standards, our TDWG standards, treat neutrally in
a flat layer. And I would like to challenge this approach in this
presentation and to offer some alternatives
to you.
Not all direct evidence is equally direct, and grammar is a surprisingly
useful lens.
If a living organism is observed, then present tense applies. It is here and now.
A shed skin or insect exuvium
justifies past simple. It was here, it no longer is.
Environmental DNA preserved in dry conditions,
we could use present perfect. It may have been here.
And environmental RNA, which degrades fast,
it is an example of present simple.
Something living is physiologically functioning at the
moment of recording.
Each of these direct evidences
are different and it
provides a different inference about presence.
And this distinction, it doesn't survive in our flat occurrence
records often. And
I would like to invite you to think if grammar can carry this much evidentiary
nuance, our data models can, too.
Decimal latitude and longitude are examples of a direct instrument-derived
readings. Whereas Darwin Core scientific name and identified
by,
these are annotations, explicitly interpretative layers.
They exist as equal status fields in occurrence records, and the occurrence itself,
the what, where, when triplet is not a raw detectable phenomenon.
It's an interpretation or a collection of detections and interpretations.
So what is an occurrence? Many people believe they don't
exist
objectively, but they do exist subjectively.
It's a detection event, an encounter between an observer or a device,
and the individual organism or a genete, together with a
taxonomic decision which results in naming.
No biodiversity record is fully independent of a human-driven act of detecting it
or of deploying a sensor.
And this is not a Darwin Core specific feature.
Similar pattern can be found in mixes,
the genomic standard.
But going in this direction historically was not an oversight.
I'm told it was a carefully considered TDWG solution,
balancing common content across a wide range of sources and
technical capacity, and likely the right solution at the time.
And the 4 billion records and many thousands of
participating institutions publishing 1 million record per day is
probably a good
symptom of the correctness of that decision then.
However, now we see a desire to accommodate more.
There is Darwin Core data package and a more experienced community at
TDWG and around TDWG.
Many discussions
about biodiversity evidence rotate around specimen and
sample, and a specimen as a labeled collection is typically one
individual, one species, with spatial, temporal, and personal attribution data on
the label. But for instance, for modular organisms or for clonal
organisms,
specimen is a nearly impossible collection type.
A fruit body or a piece of mycelium is technically a sample.
For ecologists, however, a sample is a collection
of observations plus documented protocol.
What was targeted, what was the effort spent, and
what the sampling was meant to represent.
And sample can be sub-organismal, can be a tissue, a blood, and
GGBN people developed a standard for
detailed documentation of this detail.
Sample can be organismal, it can be bulk,
representing multiple individuals, multiple genetes, and many
species in the same sample. It can be blind, like eDNA.
It could be a volume of water
collected with
its full diversity, which is invisible and unknown at the moment of sampling.
And
samples are becoming more and more important,
not only in ecology, obviously, where this is the main way to
collect evidence, but also in monitoring and technology
progress with aerial imagery, eDNA, metabarcoding.
They all provide
sampling context, which calls for tabulation documentation, and this
is how a Humboldt extension to Darwin Core was born.
Digital sequence metadata is created by processing a physical sample.
So technically, it's a digital representation of a chemical subsample from
organisms. It inherits the evidence of a physical
specimen and ecological context around it.
So the complexity grows, and
even our most primary evidence category already
provides a spectrum of situations
of
evidence types.
Museums had very complex relational databases before data
sharing and before GBIF, and historically, a single flat format
intended to provide an index, a phone book registration
of all the purposes of discoverability.
And over the time, people wanted to aggregate the index itself and
started to do occurrence downloads, and
it became the target of access and downloads
Scientifically,
from the middle of
last century, biodiversity science shifted towards analytical hypothesis
testing
approaches, and descriptive and comparative studies
declined proportionally.
But we see
an interesting new trend here with technology-driven acceleration, with
new sensors, camera traps, eDNA,
AI-assisted identification. So evidence multiply
faster
than data schemas can cope. Darwin Core data package
is a good solution now, but the pressure persists.
TDWG
originates
from library sciences,
and this is a field also built around provenance.
And in library science,
separation of primary sources, secondary sources, and interpretive means
is a routine thing.
And today, comparatively little exchange happens between TDWG
and neighboring communities such as GSC or ISO.
And we risk a bit of professional encapsulation,
perfecting our own standards in isolation.
And I invite in this talk to look around and see how others
handle
evidence.
I only had time to do some light research, but I have
collected a few examples I would like to share with you.
In criminal and forensic evidence handling, Locard exchange principle
applies. Every contact leaves a trace.
So if contact occurred, evidence exists regardless of what anyone later
concludes about this.
There is physical and trace evidence, which is familiar and comparable to
biodiversity sciences, testimonial evidence, and also expert
opinions is treated as evidence, and this is more similar, for instance, to
the IUCN
approach to biodiversity data.
Every transfer of evidence is carefully logged, timestamped, and attributable.
The system is fairly strict, and the classification dictates how evidence
is
collected.
So biodiversity data collection can ask at the point of capture
what tier of evidence this is and what inference can it responsibly support.
So
with hypothesis-driven research, it's common to know why you're collecting
the data. In citizen science and museum-based research, it's less
common.
I think the same principle should universally apply for any detections
and recording biodiversity evidence.
In archaeology,
physical context, where, how an item was found is recorded
independently of interpretation of what it means.
And every layer and cut and deposit gets its own
standardized record card described in full before any interpretation is
attempted.
Archaeologists use the Harris Matrix.
I don't really know yet what it is, but it is a standard for representing the
ordered relationship among the site observations.
I think it's about the placement and where and how items
were located against each other, and this is separate from
any interpretative narrative. And excavation is
destructive, so once you dig the context of
item location against each other and against the environment
is gone. So it's not only preservation by record
that survives. The context of a
collection
is also carefully recorded.
So field record, site report, and published interpretations, they are distinct
version and citable layers. And
reinterpretation is normal and expected, like
species re-identification in our field, and it never
overrides the primary record.
In medicine, levels of evidence pyramid is widespread,
with expert opinions and case reports at the bottom, and cohort and case
control studies in the middle, randomized trials, and systematic
reviews and meta-analysis at the top.
There is a GRADE framework. It rates confidence in a body of evidence as high,
moderate, low, and very low.
Explicit separate label not folded in the conclusion.
And GRADE also decouples evidence quality from recommendation strength.
A guideline can be a strong recommendation built on low-quality evidence,
and both facts are stated together, not hidden.
Medicine has to build this because decisions are
unavoidable regardless of how imperfect the evidence is, and patient
needed treatment anyway.
And biodiversity science and policy
share a somewhat similar situation with Red List assessments and conservation
triage and IBBIS reporting,
all
contain decisions and conclusions that needs to be drawn from imperfect evidence
and without long delay.
So a dataset could carry explicit evidence quality grade
independent of the decision that is built on top of it.
Both forensic and archaeological practice separate what was
recorded from what was concluded and preserve the primary layer
permanently independent of anyone's interpretation.
So both fields let multiple competing interpretations coexist linked back
to the same evidence. And
we have technical building blocks, identifiers, provenance
vocabularies, versioning,
data model.
And what is missing is
the
habit, the routine to treat
interpretations and detections separately.
In practical terms, for instance, for identification, we
started to discuss that it could be useful to
borrow from, for instance, molecular evidence
And build in
a set of terms that would quantify confidence
and probability of identifications being correct,
not only for machines, not only for molecular
pipelines, but also for humans.
Coordinates, dates, instrument readings,
they are primary detections. Whereas
identifications, annotations, trait assignments is interpretive layer,
which should be versions attributable, revisable by
design.
So I'm not proposing big changes, but
inviting
the audience to think about evolution of our standards and
maybe
separation of detection and interpretation terms in
two groups.
We could have better
interactions and dialogue with forensic science, archaeology, library science
in the future TWICs,
and we could perhaps stop treating recorded and concluded
as the same kind of fact.
Thank you very much for your attention. I'm happy to stay in touch.
Do we have time for one question?
I know it's-
I should tell you that Shelly's in charge.
It's just basically a turn around and we'll go through.
Yeah. So it will be one quick question for Dmitri while the next speaker...
Julie?
My colleague,
Harleet.
Ah, okay.
So is there a question for Dmitri before we press start?
We can talk confidence levels and taxon works.
Okay.
Hi, everyone.
Sorry.
Do you want to know if
she's online?
Yes. Is she online?
I don't know. I've been inside.
Yes.
Ellie's looking. So with the next talk, we'd like to-
Winchester and-
Welcome Julie Winchester, who hopefully is joining us online. Let's see.
My colleague Doug Boyer and I are the co-directors for a
scholarly 3D data repository called MorphoSource.
In this talk, I'm going to be talking about our sustainability plan for
MorphoSource. I'm sorry I can't be there in person, but I want to say thank you to
the TWIC organizers for putting all of this together.
MorphoSource is a digital repository service where researchers, museum
curators, and the general public can find, download, and upload 3D,
2D, and AV media representing objects of academic or scholarly interest,
largely natural history material, but we do have cultural heritage material
as well.
Here are some examples of 3D and 2D media types we support.
Everything from, on the left, colorized surface meshes and point clouds to, on
the right, different kinds of image series, including volume files representing the
slices of a CT scan, image collections used to make photogrammetry surface
models, and digitized serial sections from histology slides.
Below, we have some of the 2D images, which in this example include
histology sheets, photographs, and herbarium sheets.
We also support video.
When users contribute media to MorphoSource, the system automatically
characterizes and generates an interactive preview for most media types.
This includes tools for visualizing, annotating, landmarking, and
measuring both volumes and meshes.
On your left, that shows a CT scan of a fossil skull,
and on the right, this is a photogrammetry-produced 3D model of a
partial fossil skeleton that has been annotated to help explain the
anatomy. All of these preview assets are mobilized with IIIF,
providing for interoperable display of previews and
annotations.
This is a full list of the imaging modalities that the site supports, which is
increased periodically, especially in response to community requests.
MorphoSource is organizationally currently part of Duke University,
and was initially launched in 2013 as a free service.
It was originally supported by financial commitments from Duke, and since
2017, our main support has been grants from the US National
Science Foundation. Over the last decades, we have worked
closely with our user communities, as well as working groups and communities of
practice, to help build out the repository according to best
practice standards for records and metadata.
MorphoSource is, to our knowledge, the largest scholarly repository for 3D
imagery, with more than a quarter of a million datasets, where a
dataset could be a single 3D model, but it could also be the
2,000 images comprising a CT image stack.
And together, these datasets represent 96,000 specimens
associated with almost 2,000 collection object
organizations. These media are all contributed by a global
community of 2,900 data contributors, and
there are 32,000 registered users.
You have to be a registered user to download content from the site.
MorphoSource is not taxonomically restricted.
We currently have over 25,000 taxa.
Most of those are chordates, but there's a pretty decent non-chordate diversity,
and that representation is growing over time.
In terms of impact, there are a variety of ways that you could measure that.
One is by site visits and downloads.
More than a million media have actually been downloaded since 2013, and there have
been twice as many site visits just since 2021.
Based on demographic reporting from users, it's not just researchers and
graduate students that are doing that downloading.
As you can see, there's significant use related to primary school education,
by the general public, by artists.
We actually don't know of another scholarly data repository that has such broad
public engagement.
About four years ago, there was a survey that was designed to assess data
sharing and archiving habits for participants in natural
science communities, and we felt the survey showed pretty strong evidence of
MorphoSource impact. The survey was distributed through about 30 different
mailing lists, representing dozens of disciplines, and returned 750
responses, and the results have actually been published in the Yearbook of
Biological Anthropology.
Now, in this survey, one question asked participants
to enter the names of repositories they had accessed data from.
Now, surprisingly, MorphoSource essentially tied aggregated
NCBI repositories like GenBank and SRA and was
more frequently mentioned than any others.
We think that this reflects that MorphoSource mobilizes 3D data, and
does so in a way that makes them highly usable and reusable for high-impact
activities.
Another way to track impact is also to look at citations.
On the right, the green line here shows annual publications mentioning
MorphoSource, with select comparative digital resources plotted for
comparison.
At least 3,000 articles have cited MorphoSource for data deposit
or access through 2025, with about 640 of
those citations occurring in 2025.
As in the example publication in the bottom left, many articles provide DOI
links back to MorphoSource datasets.
MorphoSource has also developed a critical role in the data management
strategies of funded research, particularly from the
United States NSF. So the major NSF directorates that fund
research supported by MorphoSource are geoscience, social, behavioral
economics, and biology. If you search the NSF public abstracts for
MorphoSource, you will find over 100 mentioning it as a key
or primary informatic resource.
MorphoSource has been critical to funded and published research, but we are also
increasingly providing a critical service to museums, allowing them to discover,
take control of, and manage media associated with their collection.
At this point in time, almost 250 collections from 90 institutions
use MorphoSource's organization-level management tools to manage data.
So what does it take us to run this service?
Currently, we have four full-time employees, and that costs about
400,000 a year. Data storage accounts for another 25,000.
That's not just operating the site.
We're actually regularly doing new development to address community needs.
If we weren't to do that, if we were to operate more at a steady state, then we
would need future employees. Likely, we could run this site with closer to
300,000 a year. Generally speaking, our data storage costs go up
by about 2,500 every year.
So based on that, what does the funding landscape look like for us?
Well, as I mentioned, we have been NSF-funded, but
our current runway for current funding ends towards the end of next year.
We have some in-hand commitments from Duke, but those don't add a ton more time.
So how do we plan to keep going?
So as we started developing this sustainability or
business model,
we've known this was coming for a long time, and we've spent the last few years
developing a plan. These are some of the guiding principles that
we used in creating that model, which I will say, although we still
plan to seek federal funding, we know that NSF has strong expectations of
repository sustainability.
And so being a community-based repository, we think that it is
appropriate to rely on community support.
So we've evaluated a lot of different possible models,
and in fact, we've excluded a lot of models, just because they don't make
sense for our user community or how MorphoSource is used.
Instead, this process has led us to this following
sustainability model for covering our annual operating costs.
To cover salaries and fixed costs like server hosting, we plan to work
on raising revenue through pledges, donations from some user
communities, and subscriptions from others.
We plan to run pledge drives targeting our registered users and approach scholarly
professional societies for sponsorships.
We also plan to offer paid subscriptions to museums for access to
organization-level management features and to journals in return for a variety
of services.
Finally, we are going to recover the cost of data storage through deposit fees
required of most contributors, and I'll speak about that in a little bit.
As an open access repository where media are owned by data contributors and
museums, it goes against our mission of democratizing access to data to
ever charge for registration or data access.
But we do plan to run a voluntary user donation
drive. We're planning to start those quarterly.
And we will run our first drive in October.
So please consider contributing if you think MorphoSource is valuable.
For scholarly society memberships, MorphoSource provides
a unique resource to members of at least 12 major scholarly societies in
that publications of the flagship journals of these societies account for about a
third of all articles that cite MorphoSource.
We're currently reaching out to these societies for support, and one
society has actually already committed funds, while others are still considering.
Moving on to subscription-based revenues for museums and other academic
institutions. As I mentioned, an increasing number of museums rely on the
organization-level management features that MorphoSource provides.
Looking at the distribution of collection sizes and feature usage on MorphoSource,
we divided our subscription plans into four paid levels.
For institutions with small digital footprints, there is also a free
tier plan.
When we look at the distribution of museums currently using management features in
terms of which level they fall into, it looks like this, which is good
because we want institutions to have subscription options that
scale to the size of the institution.
For collections with small digital footprints, there is also a free tier.
In terms of timing, we have already engaged in a number of
discussions with our community, both with individual
institutions and through webinars and through emails, and we feel
like we are in a good position in terms of having communicated with our community
about the shift to this paid model.
Most of those were positively received, and we are currently cautiously optimistic.
So, for museums that have decided that they will not be
subscribing, if they are currently using management tools, they will lose access to
those in early 2027. But for institutions that
plan to join, they can actually join and pay any time during
2027. We will not turn off any management features for those
institutions.
Journal subscriptions are the final component at this point.
Morphosource using articles show up in over 480 journals from
169 publishers.
This is a part of the model that is likely going to take longer,
and we plan to start putting more pieces of it in place soon.
So what does success look like? Well, our ideal revenue
distribution would break down like you see on the left.
If you break it down,
it involves a number of museums subscribing at different levels, 12
professional societies, and 10% of users participating
in pledge drives.
What if we got a little
less or if the breakdown was different?
We would still be good because, in this case, we do have assurances from Duke in
relation to backstop.
By year five, we would love to have our operations revenue covered largely by
museums and by journals.
This would reflect a reduction in museum revenue, which would really mean that
hopefully we would be able to reduce subscription rates,
and have really more museums buy in.
That said, if we don't get to this, success could also look like this.
Even with museum revenue rising under this scenario, we hope that with more
museums joining, that that would still allow for us to reduce subscription rates
for that community.
One thing I haven't discussed is paying for data storage.
So right now, we are able to subsidize many deposits.
The level at which we are able to subsidize deposits will start to go
down over time.
And to think about longer term sustainability, we're targeting a number of
different areas. First, by adopting technologies that reduce storage and operation
costs, which we've made really good progress on this so far.
We also don't necessarily plan to always go it alone with Duke.
So we are exploring technologies and partnerships that allow scaling with
infrastructure at universities outside of Duke.
I actually have a partial secondary position with the KU Biodiversity Institute
and Natural History Museum, and there has been some interest on the KU side about
exploring a node network to spread the infrastructural hosting between both
institutions.
And similarly, we are looking at partnership tools and policies that enable that
shared effort and governance, which part of that is sharing staff with
KU. But there's also mutual interest in further
integration efforts.
And of course, we would like to explore endowments and donor opportunities as well.
Okay. In summary, we believe Morphosource provides unique value to multiple user
communities.
In fall 2026, we are going to begin raising money from these communities.
And in five years, we hope to achieve a stable portfolio of revenue sources
covering operating costs.
Long term, we hope to work towards shared infrastructure and governance.
All right. Thank you very much. That concludes my presentation.
If you would like to talk more, please reach out to either Doug or myself.
You can find our contact details through morphosource.org. Thank you.
Ellie, is Julie online or no?
I would say online.
Okay. So as I said, please do contact them for more information.
I think my comment after watching that would be, I think
we are moving away from the era of thinking of
things being provided to us for free.
And so thinking upfront about how we're going to pay for these things, because all
those organizations are going to have to come up with money from somewhere.
Yeah.
Next up, you can see Shelley is
putting out some interesting-
Bits and bobs.
Yes. Bits and bobs.
Yes. It's the Shelley and Deb show.
Yes, it is.
Welcome.
Something a little bit different.
Some of you have experienced the Shelley and Deb show before. How many have you?
How many in here? Yeah. Okay. So we have some repeat
visitors-
Yeah
... in our audience.
So yes, we are the final
talk of the session, and it's a little more interactive, getting all of you
guys involved and thinking outside the box a little bit, and then
hopefully drawing on some of the things you've seen
earlier in the session. So my name's Shelley James.
I'm the collections manager of the Western Australian Herbarium.
Julia Percy-Powell is online, so you can ask her questions as well, and
she works with me, and Deb.
And Ellie Wallace sitting here, making sure everybody online can
participate as well. And I'm Debbie Paul, and many of you will know me
from my iDigBio days as Workforce Capacity Development Manager, and
I currently work
with the Species File group. Any members here in the room?
I know Matt stepped in for a minute, but okay.
So I work with a group that works on Catalogue of Life,
TaxonWorks, and Global Names, for those of you
who are interested in managing taxon names.
Mm-hmm.
And with that,
let's talk about what we're currently doing and what we could envision
doing in terms of publishing and communications.
Yep. So this is very much an audience interaction
talk.
We're in a safe space.
All ideas, suggestions, and comments are obviously welcome,
including from our virtual participants.
So stick stuff in the chat if you're out there in the virtual world.
Shout out, raise your hand, add information to the online chat, and we
invite you to be part of this talk.
So, the first question we have to ask all of you is what do
you consider to be a publication or a product?
Obviously, journal articles, books, blog posts, gray
literature,
but there's also software, tutorials.
Are there other things out there that you think of as publications?
Anything missing?
Someone at a previous conference suggested tours are a form of
publication and communication of collections, for
example.
How many of you work on software?
How many of you use software that other people in this community
are providing for you?
Mm-hmm. Raise your hand if you think they deserve credit.
Excellent.
All right. Now you're getting into it. All right.
But what does your institution consider a publication?
Is it a little more dry? Is it only formal peer-reviewed,
non-formal
reports, and annual reports, and those sorts of things?
Is it different to what we as individuals perceive as a
publication?
Yeah.
Pretty much.
Can we change that perception?
So how many of you get credit for software that you produce?
For some reason, I think it's dataset.
Wait. Yeah.
David?
Just to add something, so for us, it's also dataset
publications. So, those are, at least within
our group,
part of ... Yeah. You get a DOI, and that makes it
obvious that it's some kind of research outcome.
Okay.
Peter, you raised your hand. How did that happen? Can you tell us?
How do you get credit for software?
Well, one thing is we also deposit those on Zenodo so it gets a
DOI, and the other is we are a team that is
involved in a lot of projects where people want software,
and so they know that that is our role in projects, and that is how we get credit
for the software. It's not expected for us to do the
publications. It's in the collaboration that we have with other people that
people acknowledge us and credit us for the expertise and the software we produce.
So it's a mix of expertise and the software we produce. That's the credit we get.
Okay.
Arthur wants to chime in.
Thanks, Ellie, for getting your steps in.
Yes.
When working in Brazil in the past, one of the issues that came up
with the funding bodies and recognition
was the directors were physicians, physics
rather, and
they publish rapidly and regularly and high
impact because the journal's finished or the
publication's finished in a couple of years and nobody reads it.
We're in the taxonomy area. We publish something
that
nobody may read for 100 years and then become important.
And it's this impact
is not immediate, but is long-term, and it's something that's
often not recognized.
Yeah. Hmm. Good point.
And yes, Peter.
One metric where you can see if a publication or one of those things is a
metric or success or a publication is, for example, if you're submitting a project
for Horizon Europe, one of the things you have to list is the expertise of
your team and is
five main publications, five projects you have worked on.
So projects is also one, which makes sense because sometimes you are
acquiring funding. But there's also one where there's other types of
outputs, and there you can list datasets and software, and that is something we
very often do. So, I would say there is a way for the
non-traditional publications to get in there and get credit.
That'd be awesome.
So the National Science Foundation has something very similar, I think.
So you can put it in there, you can put it in your CV.
I guess I'm asking, for example, for us at the local institution,
in the context of your job and your
institution, that's not always the case at that level.
Certainly at the
funding level.
Yep. Mm-hmm.
Okay. Then who is your audience?
Is it a local audience? Are you more national,
international? Is your audience always going to be leadership?
Is it students? Is it English-speaking only?
Yeah, and I think part of my question here for all of you, that I
personally feel strongly about, is are
there audiences you wish you were reaching?
For me, I see that oftentimes there's the, "Gee, I wish
this group would read this," but how do I get that publication
on their desk in front of their eyeballs? And that's not easy.
That's not a wish. That's not just if you build it, they will come.
Right?
Are there audiences you're not reaching that you'd like to, or are there audiences
missing here?
I think this and previous slides, they reveal
two quite different situations. Many of us
are brave enough to do the, "Hey, look at me now" webpages,
LinkedIn, ORCID profiles. You decorate with whatever matters to you and
try to believe that others will like it too.
Then there are formal situations, habilitation, tenure track,
professorship tracks. In University of Helsinki, it's docentship.
You need to build a portfolio
And in the Academy of Finland proposal application, you're not
free to add sections. You have certain type of publications,
certain monographs, scientific illustrations.
There are boxes given to you to fill.
There is usually one which is more liberal, like add anything else
that matters to you category, and you can put data sets there
and so on, without any guarantee that this will be checked when the
formal comparison is made.
I think this should be seen as two separate scenarios.
But I think if we mint very shiny coins of
digital recognition of our software and data outputs,
it will still not matter if
the market is not ready to receive this currency.
And at my work level, I have no influence
on how NSF or DFG works and how universities
treat the incoming professors. I know cases in the
US, like when
the most popular dataset, not a nature or science
publication, landed a permanent professorship in the American
university. So dataset mattered more than papers, but I think it's
exceptional, and I don't know how this market can change. Thank you.
Interesting. And I'm going to jump in, Arthur.
I want to add one more topic that we can think about carefully.
Recently, this is very recently, say in the last six months,
there are new professors, these early career researchers,
that have run into problems, this is a US example,
where current colleagues, senior career at those
institutions, have very strong negative feelings
about AI. So if you come in and you build your lab website,
and you put up an AI-generated image that expresses your
concept of your lab and helps you express what it is you are
excited about,
they are getting very negative feedback in their own
institutions and their departments.
It is impacting their early career status.
So this thinking about what you put out there, I'm suggesting
this is something we all need to be thinking about.
I hope that we improve how we treat each other in this space.
We are doing research, and that's what we're figuring out.
And taking it out on your colleagues for them exploring new avenues,
not really what we want to see in science.
So anyway, I'm sorry. Going back, I realize that's a tangent.
Do you want to move on to your next point?
Sure. Do you want to add a final quick thought?
Just to add something.
In my spare time, I'm also vice president of CETAF, so I'm also
dealing with the consortium of the European taxonomic facilities at large.
And we have talked a lot about the new strategic
direction of CETAF, and it was we need to engage more with the
private sector. So that's something that we need to--
When you ask who don't we reach right now-
The audience. Yeah
... it's in terms of really the private sector and how they use our data and
our outcomes, our products. And that is something that we really have
a hard time dealing with, in terms of what audience we don't
reach with our products, with our knowledge at large.
It's something that all the organizations that dealing with that should really keep
an eye on. Because the data is already used.
The bank sector is heavily using GBIF data, for example.
So it's really important to see how we connect better, and that's
actually something that our institutions also get recognition for because
there is a need to engage more with the private sector.
Yeah. And I think we could have whole sessions and invite some marketing and
communications and other people how to do this. All right.
Moving on so we don't run out of time. Arthur, can you...
We've got three minutes.
Yeah. Left? We have three minutes? We have three minutes left, Arthur.
Let us-- Yes. Okay. So,
from Pensoft point of view, I wanted to share, we are both
editors-in-chief at Pensoft, along with our two other co-editors
in chief. And we invite you to this diamond open access
to tell your colleagues, and for you, your students,
submit your articles, submit your ideas, become an editor.
It's an opportunity to get involved in that process and also to help
mentor other people who you know would be good in this role.
You can reach out to them and say, "Here's an opportunity for you." We have over
60 papers published in the first two years.
Anything you want to add?
No.
Okay.
To the Biodiversity Information Science and Standards from Pensoft,
which is the journal that TadWIG publishes, its
abstracts and longer papers are welcome,
always.
Submit your extended abstract.
Along with that, consider that the inside the Pensoft
world, they have this current tool called Arpha, this
writing tool. And in these different journals, you can experience
that sort of
one-stop shopping for authoring your paper, reviewing,
et cetera. And I'm going to talk now.
So, you want to talk about Orfo real quick?
Just real quick here.
Yep.
So, Pensoft now has a brand-new authoring tool,
it's all online.
Yeah.
Orfo. Check it out.
Afo is going to be replaced by Orfo.
So go see the Pensoft folks downstairs.
They will give you all the swag you could possibly want.
And it's a great product. So, we explored it yesterday, and it's
fabulous.
So, the cool part about that is, again, it's very interactive, pulls data
in from outside sources for you, so you don't have to.
It's very cool.
Makes life easy.
So,
Shelly brought this up earlier: How do we engage more voices?
How do we make sure on social media-- I still see a lot of groups using Facebook.
Frankly, people are on Instagram. They're on TikTok.
They are not on Facebook.
Appealing swag that is inexpensive,
appropriate, sells and tells a message, sends a story, tells a story, sends a
message.
I've got some postcards out the front that I developed. They were cheap.
They took a little bit to develop, but everyone loves them.
They disappear, so get in quick if you want them.
But Picture Eye has magnets, and there's stickers downstairs.
There's really inexpensive ways to pitch your ideas and your
products and your publications and your work to
others. And when someone says, "Oh, that's a cool sticker," you can tell the
story, and it's fabulous.
And along those lines,
consider who do you want to reach? This is another thing about
audience, right? And so your swag can have influence in new
ways.
Cool patterns that invite people to say, "What is that?" Doesn't have to be
obvious.
Is it wearable, right? Does it get around? Is it traded?
Do people covet it because it's unique, and they want one, too?
Mm-hmm.
And then there's promoting and valuing hidden collections and hidden
datasets. So I have a project working with the University of Cambridge
Herbarium, where I personally go there on my holidays, and I
digitize their collections, and I've made now 15,000 Australian
specimens come out of the dark and are now being used for
research. So thinking of different ways of
promoting those hidden collections that are out there.
And along those same lines, excuse me, consider the
workflows you have and the protocols.
Some of you do publish those on your intranets or in your own network,
but do you get them out there for the rest of us?
They can get a DOI, they can be in Zenodo in the way that Siobhan showed
us.
But they are important ways of sharing knowledge, and
a lot of times we can benefit from each other's knowledge, right?
So we've five minutes.
Got it.
Yep.
We are two more slides.
For those of you, if you're willing to still stay, which you currently are.
How many of you experienced Steam Spinach
last year at Spinach? Yep. Grant, okay.
So we raised $4,000
by getting art donations.
Money was not the point.
The point was to bring new audiences to the table,
bring out other people in the university from other departments,
economics, history, computer science, and bring them in to show
them what we do and look for intersection and overlap.
We published the model on Zenodo. You want to try it?
It's there.
And the money fed back into students coming to conferences to be able to tell their
stories.
Yes, that's where the money went.
This is one last example. Imagine right now there's an animator standing in the
back of the room, and the whole back of the room is whiteboard.
And they're animating all of our talks.
We did this at several workshops and meetings we did that I had the experience to,
or the pleasure to experience, and then we expanded on it.
So we had a workshop on natural history collections and pathogen
preparedness,
and this is an example of an animated talk. These are all on Zenodo.
You can use these. You can put them on a T-shirt, put them on a scarf,
print them wherever you want, use them in your talks. But they all have DOIs.
They're all reusable. They've been downloaded already thousands of times.
I think we've heard Siobhan talk about this, so we can skip over it pretty much.
Yay.
And then
using data datasets, can they be easier to create, publish, and
use? You mentioned publishing names to
ZooBank. There's MicroBank, IPNI for taxonomic names.
Let's get our information out there
as efficiently as we can, and there's now really cool AI chatbots
that can help answer questions that general
public want answered that they can't find any other way.
So.
And that is growing all the time.
Yes.
How can we make it easier to do this?
So with that,
what are your ideas for moving this forward?
And that's where we leave it.
Yep.
For discussion at morning tea.
Thank you.
Any thoughts now? I realize you want to go to the break, also the unconference,
if you have thoughts about this.
And thank you to all of our speakers in this session.
Okay.
I think it's time now.
Yeah. From standards to implementation, connecting
observation data in Asia to GBIF infrastructure.
My name is Kumiko, and I'll be moderating this session.
Our co-moderator is Kate and Melissa in front.
Okay. Before we begin, we would like to
acknowledge the
sponsors, and we would like to thank them.
Today, we have five speakers. Each presentation
slot is 15 minutes, including questions and discussions.
To help us keep on time, we will give speakers signals
when there are five minutes remaining, and two minutes remaining, and time's
up.
For questions, you can raise hand here in the room
or post your question on Whova, and we will keep eye on the online
participants for the questions as well.
But please note that there might be some delays, so if we
don't catch any questions from Whova from online participants, we're going to
follow up later on.
Before I move to the talks, I'd like to give a really quick
introduction about this symposium.
So this session brings together case studies from Asia
on managing and publishing biodiversity observation data, as well
as example of how these data are being used.
As Dave explained on the first day of the conference,
the world that Chadwick deals with involves much more than simply just
data standards.
It requires expertise in many different areas, and it can be
difficult for any one single person to understand everything.
But that is the one of the strength of this community.
So
there's always somebody that know
that you don't know, so you can have a communication.
So we often face similar problems and someone may
have found a solution
like
developing a useful tool or learn something through their
trial.
So here, by sharing these experiences with each other, we may
find some ideas to help us tackle our own challenges.
So many of us work with limited funding and small
project team members. So I hope
you can find something useful in today's case studies,
perhaps an idea that you can take home,
and then hope you can get some ideas back to your own
work. So I hope you enjoy this session.
Okay. So let's move on to the first part of the session.
Okay.
So our speaker is Zhujun Jiang, who will talk about the workflow for
publishing monitoring data from Taiwan.
Zhujun, the floor is yours.
Thank you.
Okay. Morning, everyone. I'm Zhujun Jiang, and I'm the
developer from Taiwan, which is one of the GBIF nodes from
Taiwan. In today's talk, I would like to share the
building a living publication workflow for long-term social
ecological monitoring data, and I'll take the Taiwan
LT-SER as an experience. But obviously we have a
terminology alert, LT-SER. So before I get
start, I would like to have a bit more introduction about
LT-SER, which stands for Long-Term Social
Ecological Research in Taiwan.
It is a site-based long-term monitoring project across Taiwan.
In this project, we collect three types
of data: ecological, environmental, and social
data. By combining these three different types of data,
we would like to have a better understanding of the impacts of
climate change and human activities.
At the same time, we also encourage each research
team to share their data and promote data reuse.
However, when it comes to
publishing long-term monitoring data, there are several
challenges. First, the dataset is growing
and being updated.
Every time we publish the dataset, it takes a lot of
time and effort to extract, transform,
and validate the biodiversity data
to align with Darwin Core terms
so that it can work with biodiversity data
infrastructure such as GBIF.
So for the
long-term monitoring data, a one-time publication is
simply not enough.
In the worst case, this data may just sit in
some data repository or data portal without
even ever reaching biodiversity data infrastructure.
So to address the issue,
Taiwan is developing the semi-automatic
data publication workflow.
The entire workflow is divided into three phases.
The left one is the first phase, where research
teams are involved in preparing and managing their data.
The middle one is the automatic workflow, where all
the jobs are handled by robots and scripts.
The final phase is publication to
biodiversity data infrastructure such as GBIF and
TBR.
I will walk through each phases in details in the
following slides.
So the first thing we did is co-designing
the LT-SER data template with each research team.
The goal of the data template is to provide a clear
definition and specification.
For example, we have field name, definition,
data type, control value, example, and requirement
status in the template.
The priority of this template is to fit the monitoring
and data collection needs of each
research team, still make it easier to
map the data to Darwin Core later on.
Then the research team can fill the data using the
data template,
and upload the data set to Deposita,
and it's where the first bit of magic happens.
Deposita serves as a data repository hub
that bridges between research data management and downstream
biodiversity publication. It provides public
APIs for both data and metadata that makes
automation possible.
And it also support different type file formats
and is openly accessible to all users.
More importantly, Deposita provides a persistent
ARK identifier to each data set, so the data
set can be referenced with stable identifier over
time. If you are interested in Deposita, you can
check the link below.
Then we move into the automated workflow.
The robot checks through Deposita
API to see whether any
data set has been updated every day at 3:00
a.m. while I'm having a good night.
If an update is detected, it will trigger the entire
workflow.
So first, the data set
is
checked to see if it follows the data template.
If it doesn't,
an email will be sent to the contact person of research
team. If everything looks good, the data will be
inserted into LT Portals database and display
on the portal.
Then the second bit of magic happens.
The data will be mapped to the Darwin Core and sync to
the Type If IPT for the following publication.
Finally, the data set was published to
the biodiversity data infrastructures such as GBIF
and TBIA
to reach different data community and TBIA,
Taiwan Biodiversity Information Alliance.
It is a platform that integrate the
biodiversity data from different
institutes and organizations from Taiwan.
If you want to know more about TBIA or how we make it happens, you
could also check the link below.
For now, we have
reached a little milestone. There are four different
data set have been published through the workflow.
These four different data set.
So finally, I would like to address that the goal of
this workflow is not a one-time publication.
We are trying to make the entire workflow living.
It means that it supports continuous data updates
across biodiversity infrastructures.
And lastly, I would like to thank for all of the support from this
organization and all your attention. Thank you.
Hello. Oh, there, it's working.
Thank you so much, Jizhon Jiang. If I-
It's great pronunciation.
Okay, got that. Thank you so much. So,
for the interest of time, if you have questions regarding his presentation,
maybe we can entertain one question.
Or later on maybe we can combine all your
great questions after
all of the presentations. Is that okay for everyone?
I think I take that as a yes. Okay.
Thank you.
Okay, so the next
presentation.
Okay, so
let me... Wait, Kumiko, I will introduce you first.
Okay, so the next presentation is
Kumiko
Tutsu from
Japan, and
her presentation is about a community-driven network for
large-scale wildlife biodiversity monitoring using camera traps.
So, yeah, take it away.
Thank you.
Okay.
Right. Okay, thank you. I'm Kumiko again.
I'm from National Institute for Environmental Studies,
Japan. I'm going to introduce about Snapshot Japan.
It's a community-driven network for large-scale wildlife biodiversity
monitoring using camera traps. And today, my colleagues could
not attend the conference, so I'm going to present on behalf
of the Snapshot Japan management team.
So first, I would like to point out
what is important for monitoring project with citizen
science. First, to keep going the project, we
need to maintain the community
to have a long-term monitoring system.
And secondly, we need
data control, quality control, for example,
species identification and all survey protocols.
Because we both have experts and non-experts to collaborate and
make sure to have a reliable species identification.
And lastly, the data standardization.
We need to share the data
beyond the individual project. We need to have an
internationally standardized format.
Camera trap research is getting really popular, and it's
used as a tool for monitoring terrestrial mammals and birds.
So the number of papers increasing every year, and it's
relatively easy to install and collect data
with relatively low cost. However,
single
camera trap can produce many
images of animals and birds in it,
and it requires a huge load of data
management and also the identification of each
individual
species.
And lately,
for example, Wildlife Insights, the data management system, is
commonly used, and we have more easy
way to
manage our large amount of image data.
And,
also the Camtrap DP, maybe most of them knows about it, but
it's a camera trap data standard format that
is internationally used, and we use this,
and then that can be published to GBIF.
So camera trap initiatives. There is Snapshot
Global, which is a network for global standardized and long-term
monitoring for ground-dwelling mammals and birds.
And there are several regional initiatives all over the
world.
This one in North America and Europe and South
America. And currently Japan is the only
regional initiative in Asian
areas.
Snapshot Japan was established in 2023 with
eight principal investigators, researchers,
and the aim of this project is to promote camera trap
research and monitoring and mobilize high-quality data
using camera traps and share this data in standardized
format.
And our community consists of quite a
wide range of sectors, including scientists and
industries, students from high schools, and citizen science group.
And these are managed by the Snapshot
Japan management team.
And now we have five members of the management team.
I'm not part of them, but I am presenting for them.
And they are the researchers, controlling this project
and yeah, maintain the community.
This shows the
Snapshot Japan project outline for the yearly annual
schedule. So the beginning of the season, we
deal with the previous year's data.
We do the quality control of the species
identification and publish data,
including all
publication. And then we get some feedback from the participant from
the previous year. And then we recruit the
members for the coming up research, which is actually
happening right now, September to October.
We set up these camera traps. So we
get the new participants or continuing
participants to keep going this project.
And then we provide some
tutorials for setting up the equipments, the camera
traps, and how to upload on Wildlife Insights and how to
identify species there.
And then, yeah, we have to make sure not just
put the camera traps, but get those data to upload it by these days.
And this is kind of requirement for these
participants.
Sorry.
Oops.
Yeah. So this shows the survey protocol.
Is a standardized protocol that used
from a couple of
the Snapshot initiatives. And
we set the camera from September to October in
these conditions. So it has to have at least eight cameras
in each site, and the cameras has to be apart
between 200 meter to five kilometer apart.
And,
we only collect images, and we don't use any food
baits or scent lures to attract animals or
birds or something like that. So we just set up in
the random placement.
And
for the site selection, we use the combination of deployment
level and habitat type. So for example,
you can choose wildlife forest or urban
grassland or some-- That kind of combination we choose for the site.
And for
continue this project, we have quite a few online
resources and services, including websites and help desk
and mailing lists and so on, the webinars that I explained before.
And we have a visualization app just only visible
for participants, but they can put the data and then see on the map.
We have a service to lend camera traps for the
group participants who needs the support.
And we get feedback from the participants about
our project to improve it. And these are managed by the team, the five
members before explained.
This shows data workflow. So what participants need to
do is basically
after setting up and finish the survey, they upload the
data to Wildlife Insights, and there you can identify
species or
maybe higher level of the identification, but you can
tag them and then do it online. And after
that, the Snapshot Japan management team will check
those data for the species identification, and we will reach more
experts on each taxonomic groups to make sure we
have the right identification. And then we
export
convert data using our tool that we developed.
You can download
by scanning this QR code. It's on GitHub that you can use as
exchange data into CamtrapDB.
And we export them and then publish as a data paper and
also as a GBIF dataset. And now we
creating some exchanging
converter for beginners because we are getting more
citizen science people who maybe don't know about the data processing
tools. So we are developing currently.
And these are the results from
2023 to 2025.
The map shows the sites that we have participants that we
put the camera traps on. So in 2023, we have
nine sites. That was the beginning of this project.
And then next year we expanded to 32 sites and then
sites in 2025. So we covered quite wide range
of Japan, including Hokkaido, Honshu, Shikoku, Kyushu, and
Okinawa.
Not only the number increased, but the diversity of the participants
increased. It starts off the researcher group,
and then we have more variety of people joining us,
like NPOs and companies
and educational
institutions, like high school students and some citizen science
group as well.
And this is the result of what we get as a
feedback from the participants. We asked why they joined this
project. And the first, the more common reason, is just
interest in our project.
And the second is the access to equipment support, which is camera trap
lending.
And thirdly, we have
comments about recommendations through research networks.
So actually, some people recommend, like, "Why don't you guys join our
project?" And that's how we get more people as well.
So
it's really important to have a practical support, something like
community building as well as
connection between the people inside a community to grow
this network.
And this shows the data publication and visualization
website screenshots. We publish data paper in
Biodiversity Data Journal,
and
the same data is published on GBIF, and those can
be viewed on the Wildlife Album, which is
run by the GBIF hosted portal. And
the final one, data visualization app, is made by
Shiny, and this is only visible to the participants that they can try out with
their data.
So now
Snapshot Global is expanded quite a wide range,
but we can see still there's some gaps in some areas,
including Asia. So hopefully we can get more
groups to join this camera trap network.
Last, I want to acknowledge all people involved in this project,
participants, organizations, and all
researchers that helps us to make this network grow.
Thank you very much.
Hello. Okay. Ah, it's working. So, thank you
so much, Kumiko. And I think we are
right on time. If you can ask questions if you want regarding... Oh, yeah.
Dimitri. Yeah.
Go ahead, please.
Microphone.
Here, here. Just a moment.
Oh, sorry. Yeah.
Hello.
Thank you very much. This is fantastic talk.
And I'm trying to pressurize Peter Desmet to make...
Is he here? Next-- Yes. To make a next version of
CamtrapDB guide which is focusing more on insects.
This is fantastic initiatives, and I have seen with my own eyes in Kanazawa
how
camera traps deployed in Japan are also capturing species interactions.
You said you're not using any baits, but they were using naturally
fruiting bushes and shrubs around Kanazawa and
detecting the frugivory of birds and mammals.
So
there is a well-known frontier in the Darwin Core that we need to handle species
interactions better. We can ask anyone in this conference.
They say, "Yes, we want it." But I think there is a potential with a camera trap
not only to capture and recognize individual species, but species pairs like
a plant and a bird. And
we don't need to go small, like with insects, but these are still large enough
that image recognition will work.
So I think this is an opportunity you have inside Japan in Kanazawa. Thank you.
Yeah. Thank you for the comment. Yes.
We want to expand
maybe the methods in the future, but right now we are following the
standard simple protocol to make it going to have a
unit integrate with the world data.
Yeah.
That would be nice. Thank you.
Okay. Thank you so much, Dimitri. And then
who else wants to ask more questions? We still have time.
Okay. So I think that's all from Kumiko,
and can we give her a round of applause?
Thank you.
Thank you so much.
Okay.
While she's still fixing her... Yeah,
okay. So our next speaker will be
Yixian Qiu.
Yes, that's correct. So
she will be talking about the reporting structure and sampling bias
correction in citizen science bird data across
Asian cities. So,
yeah, without further ado,
please.
So hi, everyone. I'm Yixian, and very pleased to be here
to share on behalf of our research team and to share some of
our recent work on the citizen science, the utilize
of the citizen science bird data across Asian cities.
So, maybe let me just briefly give some broader
context first. I'm a researcher in the Singapore-ETH
Center at the Comparative Ecology of Cities
Project. So we are a research
initiative under a cluster called Future
City Lab. So
across more than
100 cities, we bring together an
interdisciplinary team spanning urban planning,
health, biodiversity, and socioeconomic research.
So I will lead the biodiversity research within this project,
and our biodiversity work asks how urban form
and urban pattern, like landscape pattern, landscape metrics,
can shape the biodiversity that different city can
support. And why we also want to
understanding why this relationship can be
vary among cities. So to answer that, we rely heavily
on the large biodiversity database such as eBird and
GBIF. And
that leads directly to today's study.
Before using this kind of citizen science database
to interpret the urban pattern biodiversity relationship, we
first need to understand and what they actually observe
and what they may probably
systematically miss.
So the talk is from a user side, and
so we can also know that citizen science, they have
dramatically expanding the spatial extent and volume of
biodiversity observations. So infrastructures such as eBird,
GBIF, now allow us to assemble millions of occurrence records
across many cities. So it just making our large-scale research more
possible. But there is a fundamental issue.
So a point shown in the map may not just tell us
how many bird are there in the real world, because there could be
repeating counts and there could be sample bias.
And environmental can shape the latent distribution
and the richness of birds, but we do not observe
the latent biological distribution directly.
So there is ecological process like where the birds occur,
but there is also an observation and
reporting process because it's mainly being done by
the public. So where people go when they observe,
and which place are more accessible or more appealing
to observers, and how those observations are eventually
reported. So the spatial pattern we see in
the occurrence database is jointly shaped by both processes.
So based on the distinction, we organize the study as a
framework linking the ecological process to the reporting
process and automatically to the ecological
inference. So first, we're just trying to characterize
the reporting structure itself. Second, we ask which part of
the urban environment enter the record and
what determines the reporting entry and intensity.
And third, we examine whether different land use type
can contact and shape the different dimension of participation
and observer dependence. And finally, we also test whether these
reporting gaps and the bias control in the data change
the final ecological inference.
We organize the framework through the four measure
gaps. So the first is the spatial reporting support.
We will ask
where reporting occurs and where is absent.
And the second is about the environmental representation.
So even when the grid is sampled, we
need to know whether the sample location represent the
full urban environmental opportunity space.
So here, we just compare environmental distributions and the
ranges. The third is about the inventory and
observer support. We ask how much species information
those records actually support and how dependent the
resulting inventory is on particular observation
labels. And finally, we ask whether these reporting
gaps actually change the ecological conclusions.
So we use the GBIF bird data, the occurrence
data from the year 2024 across 13 Asian cities.
So after cleaning, we can retain about 2.6 million
occurrence records, and of which around 2 millions,
they were fall within the urban error pattern
analysis grids. These grids are normally, we just construct
it around two by two kilometers for each city.
And from the GBIF occurrence fields,
we mainly use coordinates and event
date recorded by which reporter, and to get
the bird occurrence records.
In addition to the birth records and reporting metrics
we calculated, we also assemble a set of urban
environmental predictors for each
grid, just to know better what kind of
spatial pattern they may
be showing up. And first, accessibility, such
as road and distance to the park. Second is about the
built-up environment, including the building
footprints and related building form metrics.
Third is about the vegetation and habitat structure because it's the
core
contribution for biodiversity. And fourth, the water context,
such as water cover and distance to the nearest water body.
So at the city level, we also use some descriptors such as the
city size, population density, GDP per
person, and something like precipitation or
seasonality, mainly to explore the cross-city heterogeneity
in reporting structure.
So maybe we can first look at the reporting itself.
So the difference among 13 cities in Asia are substantial
and are not simply difference in record volume.
So, for example, Hong Kong, Mumbai, Seoul, and
Singapore, they will cover nearly the entire study domain,
means the entire city. And generally,
we have broader observers and temporal support.
But on the other hand, cities like Beijing, Dakar, and
Shanghai, they are much thinner in both space and time
coverage. And the map also here,
in the left panel, also showing something
like the difference among cities.
So it's not just like
its reporting is organized different within cities.
And Hong Kong looks more relatively diffused, and
Singapore has one clear reporting core, while in
Tokyo and Beijing, they will contain multiple observation
hotspots.
But are the grids that enter the
dataset representative of the city as a whole?
Across the cities shown here, so the sample grids
consistently have denser roads and buildings
and are closer to the park and-- Oh, the
image doesn't show up. But
it's okay. So what becomes very visible in the data
is an access slice of the urban environment,
and this selection becomes stronger with the
city size. So as the city size grows, the
reporting occupies a progressively smaller effective
spatial footprint. So the larger cities do not simply leave
more places unobserved. Their
records become increasingly compressed into
only certain parts of the city.
And what kind of space are more likely to be recorded?
So the left panel shows a clear accessibility signal.
For example, grids with denser road network are more
likely to enter in the dataset and also receive more
reporting afterwards. Wherein the grids farther from the water show
the opposite pattern. But the park
reveals something more important.
They are always associated not only with more records but also
with more visitors and broader temporal coverage.
So far, we have shown that the reporting is
highly uneven. The next question is whether that can actually change the
biodiversity pattern we got and observed.
So to change grids more fairly, we standardize each grid to the
same support of 10 reporting events and
re-estimate the richness after that.
So before standardization, high-reporting grids appeared about
2.9 times
richer, and afterwards, the gap is
narrowed down to about 1.6 times.
So reporting density can amplify apparent
richness gradient and shape the biodiversity hotspot we
identified.
The map pair checks whether the canopy cover
and high-reporting grids and changes in richness
rank correlated.
And this is a substitute for the building height.
So we can observe high-reporting grids align more
strongly in tall building settings in Taipei.
And while in Mumbai, the pattern is weaker and differ in
different directions.
The final pair maps, this shows about
the distance to the water. So in
the cross-city screening, reporting activity generally occur
closer to water. So here we inspect
how the gradient aligns with the high reporting size and
richness changes in Taipei, also in Mumbai.
Now, return to the last issue we care about, wherein this kind of sampling
bias control the data and the biodiversity data
change the final ecological inference.
So in our previous cross-city work, we used a
city-specific GAMs model to do relating the
different key urban pattern metrics to
biodiversity. So the bubble plot displayed here-
Shows the key pattern metrics in 13 Asian city.
So each line there will tell us what is the key
positive or negative pattern metrics have their
different independent
impact on bird biodiversity.
And so this can bring us to the key first question.
If we standardize reporting intensity, does the
relationship between the same urban pattern and biodiversity also
change? So here we fix 10, means
estimating the richness using the same support of 10
reporting events to per grid. So take road density as
example. Its negative associations strengthen from about
negative 0.2 to 0.4. So with
the observation richness alone,
the relationship appears substantially weaker.
Finally, I want to emphasize the bias in the citizen
science database is not new. But the real concern is what
happens when we're trying to scale these records up for urban
and especially across cities biodiversity analysis.
This bias can propagate into different higher
ecological inference. And our results show that
the data abundance does not necessarily mean inference
support. And more importantly,
so for researchers, the key question is whether the ecological claims
we are making is safe and can actually supported by the
data we have.
So moving forward, our goal is not simply to develop more
sophisticated bias correction, but to build a systematic
framework for the research users
using opportunity biodiversity data.
By integrating better sampling event metadata, maybe we
can have a better
exploration on how we can use the opportunity data
in our future study and research.
And more broadly, I'm very interested in how
we can make biodiversity data more reliable and more useful,
from the data quality editing and the fitness for all, fitness for
use assessment to modeling.
I'm also exploring how these different data could
support ecological digital twins and more dynamic
representation of urban biodiversity.
So, if any of these overlap with your work, I will be
very happy to have a talk after this section.
And thank you, and any questions and suggestions are welcomed.
Sorry.
Thank you, Yexin, for the
nice presentation.
We can take maybe one quick question from the audience if there's
any.
There's any questions online or no?
Yeah.
Hi, thank you for your presentation. It was really amazing.
I was wondering,
when you carrying out all of this research, you are using the secondary data,
what do you find is the most difficult part on finding those
data? Which data is the most difficult, you think?
To get?
Yeah, to get.
Oh, actually, I think finding a data is not a very difficult job
because we have plenty of
facility information. But actually, it's how to do the cleaning,
processing, and how to,
especially what I mentioned, is about the sampling bias.
Because,
for all the datasets we get from near GB for eBird,
they are all reported by the
citizens public. So, the
biggest problem when I am trying to utilize the dataset,
incorporating to my research, is how we can make it
more closer to the ground truth data.
But it's very hard for us to get the ground truth data because it's
covering very large scales. So, I
still working on these
issues. So we are trying to integrate
different covariates from sampling
efforts, the spatial
autocorrelations, and also trying to
incorporate some covariates, like what I
just introduced in the slides, on the spatial structure.
So we're trying to
combine all these kind of covariate in our modeling.
So hope you can try to mitigate certain kind of
spatial bias here.
Thank you.
Thank you, Yexin. Let's give her another applause. Thank you very much.
Okay.
Our next presenter
is Jerome Chizhenko, who will share his
experience on standardizing long-term monitoring data from Taiwan in
detail.
Let's ...
Okay, so great. Hi, everyone. I'm Jerome.
I'm also from Taipei Bif as the first speaker.
And this talk is just a proposal actually, in this
stage, that we are looking to focus on long-term monitoring
datasets, the mobilizations of long-term monitoring datasets,
and we will start from moving from the already sampling event datasets
to the Humboldt Extension.
So when we are moving to a new standard, even in the past, all the
standards, we have this
idea or belief that standards will become easier to
adopt when they really return the value to the people doing the stuff, and in
this case, to the people who are doing the monitoring.
But full monitoring data mobilization is
actually a high bar, because
if we really think about it from occurrence data to event data and to
Humboldt Extension, we are asking data owners or providers to
do more and more complicated stuff.
And for monitoring data, it also
has to go through these things. It's like the project data
themselves are
basically more complex than simple occurrence data.
But when we go to the publishing systems, when we
try to fit our data into the standard, somehow we still have to
simplify some things. Some information may be lost through
this mobilization.
And in the end, especially for long-term monitoring data, I believe a
lot of people, when they share, they want this data to be
used in one way to show time series difference.
But when we want to do that kind of analysis, it still needs fine-tuning,
which actually means more work to do.
So in our experience in Taiwan, we found people are more
and more interested and motivated to share occurrence
data because they already saw the value.
And so the effort is totally worth it.
But now when we are asking them to share monitoring data, and
they realize they require higher effort to do so, but what additional value
did we really return to them when we ask them to do so?
So we have this vision that is actually quite simple.
So what kind of additional value can be given for these data
owners or to everyone? So in addition to where species
occurs, if we could mobilize monitoring data, of course, we
can then show where species increase or decreases.
But this means that actually,
to make the data owners or providers see this kind of
value, something is a little bit different, is that maybe
trend information should become available once they share the data.
This is the case when we persuaded people in Taiwan to
open their occurrence data. They see their dots on the map, and
they know how to interpret or use the map.
They immediately see the value. How can we change that kind
of thing also into the monitoring data?
So we think of this starting from what would be a
lightweight trend service needs.
So idea is actually very simple. It's just need one site, one site that
repeats it repeatedly across the year.
And what it really needs in it is that, so one comparable site,
one comparable effort,
ideally, the effort is the same across all the years.
Of course, there needs to be temporal replication, and there needs to
be a definition of the scope of the taxonomic and, of course, the
observation state. The idea is actually simple, and
in this kind of sense, we can even tell people
doing just one site of monitoring that your data is
valuable. And this is important when we talk to people who
really did their effort in one site very long time, and
previously they may think that, "I only did one site.
It's not really
worth it to share to the world." But actually, in this kind of sense, this
already means one site is valuable thing.
And when we think about this, if we focus on this kind of data, it
also eases when we move from sampling event to Humboldt
Extension. We really need to focus on just three additional
terms for if they are already published as event datasets.
So because already within these kind of projects,
surveys are repeated at the same sites,
ideally with the same spatial scope and same sampling effort.
The simple idea is what really matters now is
whether it was surveyed and whether the species in the
taxonomic scope is detected, not detected, or
if the occurrence reported is in the scope or not.
So if you know the Humboldt Extension, but if you don't know, still,
you just need, I think, the most important thing is to remember
about these three terms in the Humboldt Extension.
So the Humboldt Extension actually gives us a lot of different terms about
different scopes in our surveys. But in this kind of data,
long-term monitoring data, we believe these three are the most
important, and these are the examples.
And it could be interpreted as that the true taxonomic
scope is the target taxonomic scope minus the
excluded taxonomic scope. In some cases, like
birds and owls, owls are a subset of birds.
And then when the taxonomic scope is fully reported,
it's true.
So with this in mind, we can now look back what is already
available in Taiwan.
So for those who don't know, Taiwan is in the
quite middle of the map, in the west side of the Pacific
Ocean, somewhere here. It's pretty bright.
So this is the GBIF
open data hotspot, and this is also showing that the data
that is published through GBIF from Taiwan, we have now more than
nearly 25 million
occurrence data. So I think we're doing quite a pretty good job.
And if we're looking at the sampling event datasets,
within Taiwan, there are 140 datasets published through GBIF
now, and 52 of them are sampling event datasets.
So it's around more than 30% of that.
So when we look at 30%, we always wonder one
thing.
We people in Taiwan, maybe in Asia, we like to rank
where our position is in the world.
So we somehow try to compare, okay, are we doing quite good here?
So,
we compared
to the other large publishers to GBIF Who is
publishing more event datasets than us?
So there's Brazil, UK, and Portugal.
And if you don't like the ranking, it's just fine.
We fine-tuned it a little bit to make ourselves feel better, so you can just make
your own list to make yourself feel better.
Anyway, so we have 52
sampling event datasets. But of course,
sampling event datasets doesn't mean it's monitoring ready if you have
tried to analyze any sampling event dataset before.
So it still needs more data standards and some
fine-tuning, and of course, that's where humbled extension comes to.
To move forward, we screened all these 52 sampling event
datasets to see which are the ones we should focus on
that could fit to our focus for the monitoring reuse.
So we ask: How much work is needed before a dataset can be support for
a time-series trend?
And these are the three criteria. The first is whether they have comparable sites,
the second is whether they have comparable effort, and of course, if there's
enough temporal replications.
So
we see if the comparable sites are by survey design, which
basically means that the survey design wants the sites to be there
forever,
or the sites may not be very replicated the
same every year, but you can do it by site filtering, or you have to do
a more complicated spatial standardization, or no, you just don't know what is
going on.
And for the effort, it's
basically a very simple idea, but from site, it would
be effort filtering. And in some case, we can also do some
segmentation, because-- We'll look into that later. It will be more clear.
And of course, whether there's enough temporal replication, and we
use whether there's at least three years of
temporal replication.
In that case, for the 52 sampling event datasets in
Taiwan, we found that maybe there is 15 to be a
pretty good, strong candidate. These 15 account for
29 of all the sampling event datasets in Taiwan.
It covers years from 3 to 17 years.
Mostly are birds.
I'm a bird people, so I'm proud.
But there's also pretty good other taxos here.
So there's plants, crabs, fishes, insects, and mixed flora and
fauna.
We selected Taiwan Breeding Bird Survey as pilot one
to going to be our move-on projects to
do in the future, and the idea is actually quite simple.
So the Taiwan Breeding Bird Survey is a
large-scale citizen science survey
across all Taiwan, and its sites were designed to
be repeated every year, but sometimes because of
all kind of issues, some sites will be missing.
But anyway, it's
by design, repeated sites and repeated same effort thing.
So in this kind of thing, we already uploaded the Breeding
Bird Survey as a sampling event dataset to GBIF.
And what we really need to add to the dataset for future use is
these three terms, which we could put aves.
That is all our major targets. So every bird we
encounter in the survey, we will record it.
But we still said some of the birds we realized in
our survey design, in the method that we used, it's not very
usable or reliable for owls, which is the Strigiformes.
So we also especially inform that, and of
course, we will tell if the
taxonomic scope is fully reported.
And we also is going to choose another group of
data that's from PAM sites, which passive acoustic
monitoring sites,
as a pilot too. Because actually, if you think about it, of
course, there's a much larger effort of doing these
machine observations. And of course, we can get equal
comparable efforts out of it, but we have to do something.
So the simple idea is to do segmentation.
So what we need to do, look into these kind of
acoustic
monitoring sites, is that we
will look at the six scheduled audio, and we will see
which kind of reproducible segmentation rule can be
applied to it, and that could give us a reliable trend
output. And within that, we will be putting
these three terms into these datasets,
focusing on what these kind of
PAM would give us, which is the classifier, which is
our output target list. We could also mention some
things that we think even with the AI models we're doing to
identify the species in the PAM sites, some are
maybe not that reliable. And of course, we would
specifically state whether we have reported all the species in
our scope.
So honestly, the idea is to return useful feedback to every long-term
monitoring site,
which would hope to recognize the value of sustained
monitoring at each site. We have this prototype in mind that
we wish to give this kind of information feedback to
the users, to the data providers for each site,
that you can have a quick view of what is going on your site
once you opened your data. So you can have a quick view about
which species are increasing, which are not.
Maybe you want to see a species trend, and we
will also want to give them
index about how reliable the trend is now.
Why we do we focus things in this way is especially
as a GBIF node in Taiwan, in Asia, I think
We have this experience that we often work in contexts where managing
detailed survey structures is already challenging.
To put it straight, not a lot of data are already in
databases. A lot of them are in
personal Excels and people are
getting old,
hard disks are exploding. So we think it's something important
to give them more motivations to really put their efforts into
data mobilization. So in this sense, we hope in this
talk, we actually were thinking about this idea.
So previously, we worked on occurrence, then we worked on sampling
event. We found sampling event is not enough.
Before we work on to the full Humboldt extension, maybe we could
focus on the trend ready minimum and for the minimum
terms to give immediate feedback,
and hopefully this would give more motivation to improve structure.
So, that is all, and I would like to thank the
supporters for this project, and I look forward to have
the discussions with you guys. Thank you.
Thank you, Jerome, for the presentation. So we would like to take questions.
Thank you. This is fantastic and super timely for GBIF overall.
Kate Ingeloff in my team is doing, on the global level, what you're doing
in Taiwan, and it's
very good support and very rewarding to see it's happening.
Also, you mentioned taxonomic target as a primary
feature several times.
I was reviewing original Humboldt extension paper, and this was the
suggestion that came through the review, and I'm very happy to hear you're doing
it. However, when you market additional effort, and I fully
recognize
perhaps the
stronger need to push for more time, more effort spent in
dataset preparation.
Can you go a bit more into how declared
taxonomic target helps engagement?
Because some people may see it as a fairly boring feature.
Okay, you know what you are after in your survey. So what?
How does it help break the ice of resistance and thinking like,
"Why should I do more? Now all these stupid extensions with more terms,"
and
what's your trick?
I can't really understand how declared taxonomic target, which is extremely
important, helps the marketing.
Okay.
Yeah. So at least in our experience is that,
I believe a lot of people also knew that actually long-term monitoring for any
monitoring project to go more than 10 years,
is hard in academic institutes, at least in
Taiwan. It usually is three years, and we call it long-term, and then it ends.
So the people really doing the long-term are mostly people
in citizen science projects,
sometimes even individuals in the field, and they don't
have the tools to see what their value is
of their long-term data accumulations.
So why do I focus on the immediate feedback thing is that
they absolutely have their interest on specific species.
They
do the survey, they write down the data, but they don't see the result
very easily. If we can help them see the result easily,
maybe it will give them motivation to put it into it. Yeah.
Thank you.
Ah, there's one.
Very good exercise.
Yeah, I spent
several weeks during the summer squeezing my data into
survey
core and things like this, and it's very difficult to do
manually. You make lots of mistakes and things like this, but I was struck by the
real strong need to have an app. We have, say, on
Naturalist, we want to make an observation and get that out there.
It's quick, it's easy, it publishes straight to GBIF.
But we don't have anything, at least not that I'm aware of, that anybody can use
for putting in survey data directly in the field. Any thoughts?
Yeah.
So the idea is that we don't
currently have an immediate tool to show the values of
putting our data through the Humboldt extension.
So I think it's still the same. Previously,
we thought assembly event core is enough, so we asked a lot of people to do that.
And we tell them, "Once you do all this hard work, your effort could
be stored in the global portal, and someone,
even yourself, could easily calculate abundances,
time series difference." And then we thought that that was not
the case. So
right now,
my idea on this is that probably not focusing on all different
kind of survey data. Pick one own.
For our case, we pick the long-term monitoring data.
We focus on the needs of this kind of data use
cases. We've developed a tool to provide this
kind of direct feedback to the data providers.
So maybe in the past, we focused on a very wide range of--
We want to develop a data standard that could fit to a
wide range of different use cases.
But when we really focus on communicating with the data
providers and we want to show them the value of mobilizing their
data-
Then maybe
we focus on the specific topic.
So this is why I switched from looking at all different kind of
event data and into one specific long-term monitoring data, and
then we can ease down the terms or the difficulty
and also build a more light weighted tool
to the data providers. Otherwise, we
also cannot build a very complicated tool.
They may not also use it, and it's not going to be easy to see the result
once after they publish it.
Yeah.
Good. Thank you. So,
let's thank again, Jerome. Thank you very much.
Thank you, everyone.
So our next is the final speaker.
I can hold this one.
Yep.
Okay. So Christian Ellam will explain about the data
visualization websites in ASEAN region.
Let me open the...
Where's the mouse?
Okay. So,
good morning, everyone. I will be the last presenter for this
morning, and I will not stand between my presentation and your
lunch. So,
before anything else, let me share with you about the ASEAN
Biodiversity Dashboard. It is a GBIF-hosted portal.
It is also a regional platform maintained by the ASEAN Centre for
Biodiversity to improve access to biodiversity data and
transform those data into information that can support monitoring,
assessment, and decision-making across Southeast Asia.
So in my presentation, I will focus particularly on how the
dashboard connects species occurrence data,
protected areas, habitats, biodiversity indicators, and
other environmental information through interoperable
data system.
So,
before anything else, if some of you are not yet familiar with the
ASEAN Centre for Biodiversity, some historical background.
ASEAN Centre for
Biodiversity, or ACB, was established
in 2005 with the 10 ASEAN member states, and
recently Timor-Leste joined us last year, last October.
So we are now 11 member states. So these are
11 countries who are joining the ASEAN members,
and our headquarters is in Indonesia.
So one of the ACB's role is facilitate cooperation
among ASEAN member states, and of course, we also
promote collaboration and commitments to the Convention on
Biological Diversity as a TSCC,
and we also promote synergy with other global multilateral
environmental
agreements.
So,
why a regional biodiversity data matters?
So first of all, one of ACB's mandate is to
mainstream and mobilize biodiversity data in the ASEAN region.
And my department is one
technical arm that handles such technical activities by organizing
biodiversity data mobilization across ASEAN member states.
So our main focus there is to
organize
biodiversity data mobilization across ASEAN.
And we also
provide scientific inputs to conservations and management.
And we also provide scientific base information in the development of regional
platforms such as
national CHM and country reports within the ASEAN region.
And also support the development of project
platforms and maintain databases across the ASEAN, and we also provide,
of course,
twice or annual
biodiversity data mobilization across the ASEAN.
So,
ASEAN is one of the world's
most biodiverse region, but unfortunately,
biodiversity information, some of them are not yet in a
centralized platform, and the information is
distributed across many countries and
institutions.
So some research projects, collections, and platforms are
in different formats, and the challenge there is
not simply the lack of data, but a major challenge is making
existing data discoverable, interoperable, and reusable and
useful across not only for the ASEAN but for the global
community.
And then this is where biodiversity informatics becomes more important.
So we need to move beyond simply by
storing datasets and create a data value chain from data
mobilization and data standardization to integration,
analysis, visualization, and ultimately decision
support. So
currently, our current bioinformatics structure at ACB,
we have our own new two servers that
host the IPT and our ASEAN biodiversity dashboard.
So we recently purchased
top-of-the-line server to host our dashboard
and our integrated publishing toolkit.
And we usually publish data
from other ASEAN member states to GBIF platform and OBIS.
These are the five layers of our
infrastructure. We have
data providers from the ASEAN member states. We have data ingestions.
We also have data cleaning
in-house. And then we also have the central biodiversity
infrastructure at this one.
So this is the level of where our data is being managed and
organized in our headquarters in the Philippines.
And we also provide knowledge products.
One of which is the ASEAN Biodiversity Dashboard, the ASEAN Clearinghouse
Mechanism,
thematic portals. We have our own knowledge management platforms.
We have our own several
dashboards that requires a customizable
reporting based from the country requirements.
If they want to ask something, they want to
request ACB to provide this kind of information, we can generate
platform or dashboard, and then they will use that as a country report in
their own institution. And lastly, one of our
audience or our end users are policymakers,
researchers, and
citizen science and non-scientists, of course.
So
this is our
dashboard, and the
ASEAN Biodiversity Dashboard is designed as
more than a biodiversity repository.
It also provides a
regional environment where different biodiversity environmental data
sets can be brought together and visualized.
So at its core are species occurrence,
but this can be combined with protected areas, ASEAN Heritage Parks,
habitat information, and cover change.
We also include carbon information and other spatial data sets.
So
the objective is to create a bridge between
biodiversity data and the information needed by scientists,
conservation practitioners, policymakers in reporting processes.
So this is perhaps the most important concept behind the dashboard.
We see biodiverse information as a value chain, and first,
we mobilize data from countries and institutions.
Second, we standardize those data using internationally recognized approaches
such as Darwin Core.
The data can be published through systems such as GBIF and OBIS
and connected to the ASEAN Clearinghouse Mechanism.
So once these data sets are integrated, we
can analyze
species distribution modeling,
trends, data gaps, and biodiversity indicators.
And finally,
we visualize the results through maps and dashboard, and that
can support conservation planning, nationally biodiversity
strategies and monitoring of the KMGBF framework or
KMGBF.
With all this kind of information,
we can easily monitor and check
where has the species recorded,
how has its known distribution changed.
Is it the species within the protected area or the ASEAN
Heritage Parks?
Which
areas have insufficient observations?
Which species are associated with particular habitats?
And
where are important biodiversity data gaps?
So
from this one, as you can see, majority of our data
sets are coming from birds. So I've heard this last year
that GBIF is a global birds information facility, not
the global biodiversity information.
So the majority of our data sets are, I think it's 80% more than
that, more on birds data. So
the rest
are amphibians, reptiles, and other
taxa.
And with this kind of information, we can overlay
several layers like carbon emission within that
protected areas or HP. And we can also analyze what kind of
information needed for the country reports for them to support their
reporting mechanism to be submitted to the CBD.
Okay. So
by transforming species occurrence records
into meaningful indicators, the ASEAN Biodiversity Dashboard support
improve biodiversity reporting under the KMGBF.
So
including ACB role as a TSEC center or
technical support. How do you remember that?
Technical Support and Coordination Center of the
CBD, the TSEC. So the platform also enables
opportunities
for harmonized restoration monitoring across the ASEAN region.
We also data-driven restoration planning and adaptive management
through species distribution modeling, carbon emission assessment,
and biodiversity indices for ASEAN Heritage Park.
So we can strengthen evidence-based conservation, and ultimately
our goal is to promote stronger regional cooperation,
improve data sharing, and support more effective biodiversity monitoring
and decision-making across ASEAN.
So these are some just of the
customized dashboard that we generate based on the requirements and
needs of our
ASEAN member states.
Okay, so
one of the strengths of the dashboard is being hosted by the GBIF
secretariat is the ability to bring different data sets together.
Like for example the
speciality.
And then for example species occurrence records can be viewed
together with protected areas. It's an overlay and ASEAN Heritage
Park. AHP is one of our
flagship program. Just like World Heritage Park, we are the one
declaring
if that particular protected area fits to be an ASEAN
Heritage Park. So this allows us to ask whether particular
species are represented within protected areas and identify
potential information gaps and identify locations
where additional monitoring may be useful.
So one of the value comes not from any single data sets, but from the
relationship between
data sets. So
of course, the ultimate purpose of
our biodiverse informatics at ACB is not technology for its own sake.
The data should support the implementation of biodiversity
policies and commitments. The same
standardized data sets can
potentially
contribute to national biodiverse strategies like the KMGBF.
So the CBD clearing house mechanism, protected area
monitoring, ASEAN Heritage Parks in global infrastructure such as
GBIF and OBIS, and then interoperability, therefore
allows one investment in data mobilization to generate multiple
benefits. So these are our
main users.
We include national governments,
policy reporting, most of it are policy makers in ASEAN.
These are politicians and government officials.
And the other one is inter and non-government
organizations.
One of the advantage of ACB is we have
the arm, we have the power to
communicate within the ASEAN member states.
These are high level environmental ministries.
And then the other one is corporate sector.
Of course, we are mainstreaming biodiversity in a corporate sector.
That includes business, infrastructure, health, and agriculture.
And lastly is research bodies. We also provide technical support.
ACB is one of the technical arm that provides
technical support. We have our scientific advisory committee.
And next week, we'll be organizing a biodiversity science forum
in Malaysia. It is something like this.
So it is a huge conference that we invited all of the ASEAN member states
to
have a symposium, have the same as set up like this one in
Tadig.
And
of course,
my takeaway, our takeaway at the ACB,
looking forward, of course, our ambition is to continue
evolving the ASEAN Biodiversity Dashboard with the help, of course, from our
community, from the GBIF community, which brings
help a lot in our institution.
This means mobilizing more data, improving
interoperability, strengthening analytical capabilities,
developing biodiverse indicators, and creating more useful
visualization mechanism. So most importantly, we
want to make sure that biodiversity data collected by researchers,
institutions, and governments can ultimately contribute to better conservation
decisions. So
the future of biodiversity data monitoring is therefore
not simply about having more data.
It is about connecting data, making them interoperable,
analyzing them appropriately, and turning them into
evidence-based and action-based information.
With that, thank you so much, and that's my presentation.
Thank you, Kit, for the presentation. Any question from the floor?
Okay. Then let's thank again, Kit, for the final
presentation.
So, okay. So this concludes our session.
So, before everyone leaves, can speakers come in the front to take an
official photo for the session? So,
I hope you enjoyed, and thank you very much for joining this session, presenters
and online participants. Thank you very much.